<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posted in 2016</title>
  <updated>2022-06-14T19:29:20.012993+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/2016/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.25">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0518.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.18</title>
    <updated>2016-01-16T11:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-18"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release mainly has a scalability focus. While there are few
compatibility improvements, the larger goal has been to make Nuitka
compilation and the final C compilation faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: The nested arguments functions can now be called using
their keyword arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;someFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;someFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;.1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: Generators with Python3.4 or higher now also have a
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__del__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; attribute, and therefore properly participate in
finalization. This should improve their interactions with garbage
collection reference cycles, although no issues had been observed so
far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Was outputting command line arguments debug information at
program start. Fixed in 0.5.17.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Code generated for parameter parsing is now a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; less verbose.
Python level loops and conditionals to generate code for each
variable has been replaced with C level generic code. This will speed
up the backend compilation by a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Function calls with constant arguments were speed up specifically, as
their call is now fully prepared, and yet using less code. Variable
arguments are also faster, and all defaulted arguments are also much
faster. Method calls are not affected by these improvements though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nested argument functions now have a quick call entry point as well,
making them faster to call too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in, and internal creation of slices (e.g. in
re-formulations of Python3 slices as subscripts) cannot raise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Avoid inclusion of bytecode of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unittest.test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sqlite3.test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;distutils.test&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ensurepip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. These are
not needed, but simply bloat the amount of bytecode used on e.g.
macOS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speed up compilation with Nuitka itself by avoid to copying and
constructing variable lists as much as possible using an always
accurate variable registry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nested argument functions of Python2 are now re-formulated into a
wrapping function that directly calls the actual function body with
the unpacking of nested arguments done in nodes explicitly. This
allows for better optimization and checks of these steps and
potential in-lining of these functions too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unified slice object creation and built-in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;slice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; nodes, these
were two distinct nodes before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code generation for all statement kinds is now done via
dispatching from a dictionary instead of long &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;elif&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; chains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Named nodes more often consistently, e.g. all loop related nodes
start with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Loop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; now, making them easier to group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parameter specifications got simplified to work without variables
where it is possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="organisational"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organisational&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nuitka is now available on the social code platforms gitlab as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long standing weaknesses have been addressed in this release, also quite
a few structural cleanups have been performed, e.g. strengthening the
role of the variable registry to always be accurate, is groundlaying to
further improvement of optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this release cycle was mostly dedicated to performance of the
actual compilation, and more accurate information was needed to e.g. not
search for information that should be instant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upcoming releases will focus on usability issues and further
optimization, it was nice however to see speedups of created code even
from these scalability improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0518.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-01-16T11:41:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-progress-winter-2015.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Progress in 2015</title>
    <updated>2016-01-29T08:08:54+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-progress-in-2015"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For quite a bit, there have been no status posts, not for lack of news,
but a lot has happened indeed. I just seem to post a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more to the
mailing list than I do here. Especially about unfinished stuff, which is
essentially for a project like Nuitka everything that’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I previously said, I am shy to make public postings about
unfinished stuff and that’s going to continue. But I am breaking it, to
keep you up to date with where Nuitka has been going lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with release focuses, I have been making some actual changes that I
think are worth talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-progress-in-2015" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka Progress in 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#ssa-single-state-assignment-form" id="id2"&gt;SSA (Single State Assignment Form)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#function-inlining" id="id3"&gt;Function Inlining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#scalability" id="id4"&gt;Scalability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#parameter-parsing" id="id5"&gt;Parameter Parsing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#variable-error-messages" id="id6"&gt;Variable Error Messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#code-objects" id="id7"&gt;Code Objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimization" id="id8"&gt;Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#compatibility" id="id9"&gt;Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance" id="id10"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#graphs-and-benchmarks" id="id11"&gt;Graphs and Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#standalone" id="id12"&gt;Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#other-stuff" id="id13"&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#europython-2015" id="id14"&gt;EuroPython 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#funding" id="id15"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#collaborators" id="id16"&gt;Collaborators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#videos" id="id17"&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id18"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#future" id="id19"&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#release-focus" id="id20"&gt;Release Focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#summary" id="id21"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="ssa-single-state-assignment-form"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;SSA (Single State Assignment Form)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SSA using release has been made last summer. Recent releases have
lifted more and more restrictions on where and now it is applied and
made sure the internal status is consistent and true. And that trend is
going to continue even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For shared variables (closure variables and module variables), Nuitka is
still too conservative to make optimization. Code does annotate value
escapes, but it’s not yet trusting it. The next releases will focus on
lifting that kind of restriction, and for quality of result, that will
mean making a huge jump ahead once that works, so module variables used
locally a lot will become even faster to use then and subject to static
optimization too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="function-inlining"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Function Inlining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When doing my talk to EuroPython 2015, I was demoing it that, and
indeed, what a break through. The circumstances under which it is done
are still far too limited though. Essentially that ability is there, but
will not normally be noticeable yet due to other optimization, e.g.
functions are most often module variables and not local to the using
function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More code generation improvements will be needed to be able to inline
functions that might raise an exception. Also the “cost” of inlining a
function is also very much an unsolved issue. It will become the focus
again, once the SSA use as indicated above expands to module variables,
as then inlining other things than local functions will be possible too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is a lot of things to do for this to really make a difference
to your programs. But it’s still great to have that part solved so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="scalability"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Scalability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="parameter-parsing"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Parameter Parsing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent releases have replaced some of the oldest code of Nuitka, the one
that generated special argument parsing for each function individually,
now replaced with generic code, that surprisingly is often even faster,
although quick entry points were tough to beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gives the C backend compiler a much easier time. Previously 3 C
functions were created per Python level function, two of which could get
really big with many arguments, and these are no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="variable-error-messages"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Variable Error Messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something similar was going on with variable error messages. Each had
their exception value pre-computed and created at module load time. Most
of these are of course unused. This has been replaced with code that
generates it on the fly, resulting in a lot less constants code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="code-objects"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Code Objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And another thing was to look after code objects, of which there often
were two for each Python level function. The one used or the frame
during run time and the one used in the function object, differered
often, sometimes by small things like flags or local variable names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That of course was just the result of not passing that along, but
created cached objects with hopefully the same options, but that not
being true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolving that, and sharing the code object used for creation and then
the frame is gives less complex C code too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scalability of Nuitka also depends much on generated code size. With
the optimization become more clever, less code is generated, and that
trend will continue as more structural optimization are applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time e.g. an exception is identified to not happen, this removes
the corresponding error exits from the C code, which then makes it
easier for the C compiler. Also more specialized code as we now have or
dictionaries, is often less complex to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="compatibility"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important things have happened here. Full compatibility mode is planned
to not be the default anymore in upcoming releases, but that will only
mean to not be stupid compatible, but to e.g. have more complete error
messages than CPython, more correct line numbers, or for version
differences, the best Python version behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stable release has full support for Python 3.5, including the new
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;async&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;await&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; functions. So recent releases can pronounce it
as fully supported which was quite a feat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure, if you can fully appreciate the catch up game needed to
play here. CPython clearly implements a lot of features, that I have to
emulate too. That’s going to repeat for every major release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that the function type of Nuitka is now specialized to
the generators and classes, and that was a massive cleanup of its core
that was due anyway. The generators have no more their own function
creation stuff and that has been helpful with a lot of other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another focus driven from Python3, is to get ahead with type shape
tracing and type inference of dictionary, and value tracing. To fully
support Python3 classes, we need to work on something that is a
dictionary a-like, and that will only ever be efficient if we have that.
Good news is that the next release is making progress there too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="graphs-and-benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Graphs and Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also presented this weak point to EuroPython 2015 and my plan on how
to resolve it. Unfortunately, nothing really happened here. My plan is
still to use what the PyPy people have developed as vmprof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that is not progressing, and I could need help with that definitely.
Get in contact if you think you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="standalone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standalone mode of Nuitka was pretty good, and continued to improve
further, but I don’t care much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-stuff"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="europython-2015"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;EuroPython 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a blast. Meeting people who knew Nuitka but not me was a
regular occurrence. And many people well appreciate my work. It felt
much different than the years before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to present Nuitka’s function in-lining indeed there, and this
high goal that I set myself, quite impressed people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I made many new contacts, largely with the scientific community. I
hope to find work with data scientists in the coming years. More amd
more it looks like my day job should be closer to Nuitka and my
expertise in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="funding"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka receives the occasional &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;donation&lt;/a&gt; and those make me very happy.
As there is no support from organization like the PSF, I am all on my
own there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I want to travel to Europython 2016. It would be sweet if
aside of my free time it wouldn’t also cost me money. So please consider
donating some more, as these kind of events are really helpul to Nuitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="collaborators"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Collaborators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka is making more and more break through progress. And you can be a
part of it. Now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can join and should do so now, just &lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/user-manual.html#join-nuitka"&gt;follow this link&lt;/a&gt; or become part of
the mailing list (since closed) and help me there with request I make,
e.g. review posts of mine, test out things, pick up small jobs, answer
questions of newcomers, you know the drill probably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="videos"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Youtube channel of mine with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLKO58t9ADuF6o_Dcmve1DXpUkUEEVvDux"&gt;all the videos of Nuitka so far&lt;/a&gt;
and I have been preparing myself with proper equipment to make Videos of
Nuitka, but so far nothing has come out of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do however really want to change that. Let’s see if it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have started to use &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen"&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; on occasions. You are welcome to follow
me there. I will highlight interesting stuff there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id19"&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there is multiple things going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type Inference&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With SSA in place, Nuitka starts to recognize types, and treat things
that work something assigned from &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in with
special nodes and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s going to be a lot of work. For &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; there
are very important use cases, where the code can be much better. But
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the hardest case, and to get the structure of shape
tracing right, we are going there first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shape Analyisis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan for types, is not to use them, but the more general shapes,
things that will be more prevalent than actual type information in a
program. In fact the precise knowledge will be rare, but more often,
we will just have a set of operations performed on a variable, and be
able to guess from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape analysis will begin though with concrete types like &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.
The reason is that some re-formulations like Python3 classes should
not use locals, but dictionary accesses throughout for full
compatibility. Tracing that correctly to be effectively the same code
quality will allow to make that change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plug-ins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I wish I could have shown at EuroPython was plug-ins to
Nuitka. It has become more complete, and some demo plug-ins for say
Qt plugins or multiprocessing, are starting to work, but it’s not
progressing recently. The API will need work and of course
documentation. Hope is for this to expand Nuitka’s reach and appeal
to get more contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be sweet, if there were any takers, aiming to complete these
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nested frames&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One result of in-lining will be nested frames still present for
exceptions to be properly annotated, or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;locals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving different
sets of locals and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cleanup of these will be needed for code generation and SSA to
be able to attach variables to some sort of container, and for a
function to be able to reference different sets of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know, if you are willing to help. I really need that help to make
things happen faster. Nuitka will become more and more important only.
And with your help, things will be there sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="release-focus"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id20"&gt;Release Focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I have started recently, is to make changes to Nuitka focused
to just one goal, and to only deal with the rare bug in other fields,
but not much else at all. So instead of across the board improvements in
just about everything, I have e.g. in the last release added type
inference for dictionaries and special nodes and their code generation
for dictionary operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This progresses Nuitka in one field. And the next release then e.g. will
only focus on making the performance comparison tool, and not continue
much in other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way, more “flow” is possible and more visible progress too. As an
example of this, these are the focuses of last releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full Python 3.5 on a clean base with generators redone so that
coroutines fit in nicely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scalability of C compilation with argument parsing redone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next release soon: Shape analysis of subscript usages and
optimization to exact dictionaries&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next release thereafter: Comparison benchmarking (vmprof, resolving C
level function identifiers easier)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other focuses will also happen, but that’s too far ahead. Mostly like
some usability improvements will be the focus of a release some day.
Focus is for things that are too complex to attack as a side project,
and therefore never happen although surely possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging into Python3.5 coroutines and their semantics was hard enough,
and the structural changes needed to integrate them properly with not
too much special casing, but rather removing existing special cases
(generator functions) was just too much work to ever happen while also
doing other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id21"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am very excited about Nuitka. It feels like the puzzle is coming
together finally, with type inference becoming a real thing. And should
dictionaries be sorted out, the real important types, say &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for
scientific use cases, or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for others, will be easy to
make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, and then harder import association (knowing what other
modules are), and module level SSA tracing that can be trusted, we can
finally expect Nuitka to be generally fast and deserve to be called a
compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That will take a while, but it’s likely to happen in 2016. Let’s see if
I will get the funding to go to EuroPython 2016, that would be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-progress-winter-2015.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>For quite a bit, there have been no status posts, not for lack of news,
but a lot has happened indeed. I just seem to post a lot more to the
mailing list than I do here. Especially about unfinished stuff, which is
essentially for a project like Nuitka everything that’s going on.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2016-01-29T08:08:54+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0519.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.19</title>
    <updated>2016-02-02T09:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-19"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release brings optimization improvements for dictionary using code.
This is now lowering subscripts to dictionary accesses where possible
and adds new code generation for known dictionary values. Besides this
there is the usual range of bug fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix, attribute assignments or deletions where the assigned value or
the attribute source was statically raising crashed the compiler.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix, the order of evaluation during optimization was considered in
the wrong order for attribute assignments source and value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Fix, when &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;g++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the path, it was not used
automatically, but now it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Detect the 32 bits variant of MinGW64 too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3.4: The finalize of compiled generators could corrupt
reference counts for shared generator objects. Fixed in 0.5.18.1
already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3.5: The finalize of compiled coroutines could corrupt
reference counts for shared generator objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a variable is known to have dictionary shape (assigned from a
constant value, result of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in, or a general dictionary
creation), or the branch merge thereof, we lower subscripts from
expecting mapping nodes to dictionary specific nodes. These generate
more efficient code, and some are then known to not raise an
exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;someFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above function is not yet fully optimized (dictionary key/value
tracing is not yet finished), however it at least knows that no
exception can raise from assigning &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;value[&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; anymore and creates
more efficient code for the typical &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of “logical” sharing during optimization has been replaced
with checks for actual sharing. So closure variables that were
written to in dead code no longer inhibit optimization of the then no
more shared local variable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global variable traces are now faster to decide definite writes
without need to check traces for this each time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No more using “logical sharing” allowed to remove that function
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using “technical sharing” less often for decisions during
optimization and instead rely more often on proper variable registry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Connected variables with their global variable trace statically avoid
the need to check in variable registry for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Removed old and mostly unused “assume unclear locals” indications, we
use global variable traces for this now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release aimed at dictionary tracing. As a first step, the value
assign is now traced to have a dictionary shape, and this this then used
to lower the operations which used to be normal subscript operations to
mapping, but now can be more specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making use of the dictionary values knowledge, tracing keys and values
is not yet inside the scope, but expected to follow. We got the first
signs of type inference here, but to really take advantage, more
specific shape tracing will be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0519.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-02-02T09:04:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0520.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.20</title>
    <updated>2016-03-21T09:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-20"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is mostly about catching up with issues. Most address
standalone problems with special modules, but there are also some
general compatibility corrections, as well as important fixes for
Python3.5 and coroutines and to improve compatibility with special
Python variants like Anaconda under the Windows system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone Python3.5: The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;_decimal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module at least is using a
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; that doesn’t match the name at load time, causing
programs that use it to crash.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: For Python3.3 the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__loader__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; attribute is now set
in all cases, and it needs to have a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__module__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; attribute. This
makes inspection as done by e.g. &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;flask&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; working.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Added missing hidden dependencies for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Tkinter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module,
adding support for this to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Detecting the Python DLL and EXE used at compile time and
preserving this information use during backend compilation. This
should make sure we use the proper ones, and avoids hacks for
specific Python variants, enhancing the support for Anaconda,
WinPython, and CPython installations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--python-debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; flag now properly detects if the run
time is supporting things and error exits if it’s not available. For
a CPython3.5 installation, it will switch between debug and non-debug
Python binaries and DLLs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Added plug-in for the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Pwm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; package to properly combine
it into a single file, suitable for distribution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Packages from standard library, e.g. &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xml&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; now have
proper &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__path__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; as a list and not as a string value, which breaks
code of e.g. PyXML.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Added missing dependency of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;twisted.protocols.tls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3.5: When finalizing coroutines that were not finished, a
corruption of its reference count could happen under some
circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Added missing DLL dependency of the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;uuid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module at
run time, which uses ctypes to load it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="new-features"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added support for Anaconda Python on this Linux. Both accelerated and
standalone mode work now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added support for standalone mode on FreeBSD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The plug-in framework was expanded with new features to allow
addressing some specific issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moved memory related stuff to dedicated utils package
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka.utils.MemoryUsage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; as part of an effort to have more
topical modules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plugins how have a dedicated module through which the core accesses
the API, which was partially cleaned up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No more “early” and “late” import detections for standalone mode. We
now scan everything at the start.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release focused on expanding plugins. These were then used to
enhance the success of standalone compatibility. Eventually this should
lead to a finished and documented plug-in API, which will open up the
Nuitka core to easier hacks and more user contribution for these topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0520.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-03-21T09:34:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0521.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.21</title>
    <updated>2016-04-25T12:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-21"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release focused on scalability work. Making Nuitka more usable in
the common case, and covering more standalone use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Support for newer MinGW64 was broken by a workaround for
older MinGW64 versions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: Added support for the (unofficial) C-Python API
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Py_GetArgcArgv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; that was causing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;prctl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module to fail loading
on ARM platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: The proper error message template for complex call
arguments is now detected as compile time. There are changes coming,
that are already in some pre-releases of CPython.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Wasn’t properly ignoring &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Tools&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and other directories
in the standard library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="new-features"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Detect the MinGW compiler arch and compare it to the Python
arch. In case of a mismatch, the compiler is not used. Otherwise
compilation or linking gives hard to understand errors. This also
rules out MinGW32 as a compiler that can be used, as its arch doesn’t
match MinGW64 32 bits variant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compile modules in two passes with the option to specify which
modules will be considered for a second pass at all (compiled without
program optimization) or even become bytecode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The developer mode installation of Nuitka in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;develop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mode with
the command &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;-e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka_git_checkout_dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is now
supported too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Popular modules known to not be performance relevant are no longer C
compiled, e.g. &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;numpy.distutils&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and many others frequently
imported (from some other module), but mostly not used and definitely
not performance relevant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The progress tracing and the memory tracing and now more clearly
separate and therefore more readable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moved RPM related files to new &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rpm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moved documentation related files to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Converted import sorting helper script to Python and made it run
fast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="organisational"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organisational&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Buildbot infrastructure for Nuitka was updated to Buildbot 0.8.12
and is now maintained up to date with Ansible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upgraded the Nuitka bug tracker to Roundup 1.5.1 to which I had
previously contributed security fixes already active.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added SSL certificates from Let’s Encrypt for the web server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release advances the scalability of Nuitka somewhat. The two pass
approach does not yet carry all possible fruits. Caching of single pass
compiled modules should follow for it to become consistently fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More work will be needed to achieve fast and scalable compilation, and
that is going to remain the focus for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0521.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-04-25T12:54:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0522.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.22</title>
    <updated>2016-08-17T14:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-22"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is mostly an intermediate release on the way to the large
goal of having per module compilation that is cacheable and requires far
less memory for large programs. This is currently in progress, but
required many changes that are in this release, more will be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also contains a bunch of bug fixes and enhancements that are worth to
be released, and the next changes are going to be more invasive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: Classes with decorated &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; functions could
miss out on the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; decorator that is implicit. It’s now
applied always, unless of course it’s already done manually. This
corrects an issue found with Pandas. Fixed in 0.5.22.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: For at least Python 3.4 or higher, it could happen that
the locale needed was not importable. Fixed in 0.5.22.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: Do not falsely assume that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; expressions cannot
raise on boolean expressions, since those arguments might raise
during creation. This could lead to wrong optimization. Fixed in
0.5.22.2 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Standalone: Do not include system specific C libraries in the
distribution created. This would lead to problems for some
configurations on Linux in cases the glibc is no longer compatible
with newer or older kernels. Fixed in 0.5.22.2 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--recurse-directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; option didn’t check with decision
mechanisms for module inclusion, making it impossible to avoid some
things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduced specialized constant classes for empty dictionaries and
other special constants, e.g. “True” and “False”, so that they can
have more hard coded properties and save memory by sharing constant
values.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “technical” sharing of a variable is only consider for variables
that had some sharing going in the first place, speeing things up
quite a bit for that still critical check.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Memory savings coming from enhanced trace storage are already visible
at about 1%. That is not as much as the reloading will mean, but
still helpful to use less overall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The global variable registry was removed. It was in the way of
unloading and reloading modules easily. Instead variables are now
attached to their owner and referenced by other users. When they are
released, these variables are released.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global variable traces were removed. Instead each variable has a list
of the traces attached to it. For non-shared variables, this allows
to sooner tell attributes of those variables, allowing for sooner
optimization of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No longer trace all initial users of a variable, just merely if there
were such and if it constitutes sharing syntactically too. Not only
does this save memory, it avoids useless references of the variable
to functions that stop using it due to optimization.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create constant nodes via a factory function to avoid non-special
instances where variants exist that would be faster to use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moved the C string functions to a proper &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka.utils.CStrings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
package as we use it for better code names of functions and modules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Made &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;functions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and explicit child node of modules, which makes
their use more generic, esp. for re-loading modules.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have a dedicated function for building frame nodes, making it easier
to see where they are created.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is the result of a couple of months work, and somewhat
means that proper re-loading of cached results is becoming in sight. The
reloading of modules still fails for some things, and more changes will
be needed, but with that out of the way, Nuitka’s footprint is about to
drop and making it then absolutely scalable. Something considered very
important before starting to trace more information about values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This next thing big ought to be one thing that structurally holds Nuitka
back from generating C level performance code with say integer
operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0522.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-08-17T14:35:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0523.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.23</title>
    <updated>2016-10-03T16:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-23"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is focusing on optimization, the most significant part for
the users being enhanced scalability due to memory usage, but also break
through structural improvements for static analysis of iterators and the
debut of type shapes and value shapes, giving way to “shape tracing”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix support Python 3.5.2 coroutine changes. The checks got added for
improved mode for older 3.5.x, the new protocol is only supported
when run with that version or higher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix, was falsely optimizing away unused iterations for non-iterable
compile time constants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;iter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# needs to raise.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3: Fix, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;eval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; must not attempt to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;strip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; memoryviews. The
was preventing it from working with that type.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fix, calling &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; without any arguments was crashing the
compiler. Also the exception raised for anything but 1 or 3 arguments
was claiming that only 3 arguments were allowed, which is not the
compatible thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3.5: Fix, follow enhanced error checking for complex call
handling of star arguments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compatibility: The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;x,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; re-formulation was doing
two &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__import__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; calls instead of re-using the module value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uses only about 66% of the memory compared to last release, which is
very important step for scalability independent of re-loading. This
was achieved by making sure to break loop traces and their reference
cycle when they become unused.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Properly detect the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; of multiplications at compile time from
newly introduces value shapes, so that this is e.g. statically
optimized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;*&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10000000000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to newly introduced type shapes, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;iter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; now
properly detect more often if values will raise or not, and warn
about detected raises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;iter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;something&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Will always raise&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to newly introduced “iterator tracing”, we can now properly
detect if the length of an unpacking matches its source or not. This
allows to remove the check of the generic re-formulations of
unpackings at compile time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Will never raise due to unpacking&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Will always raise, 3 items cannot unpack to 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added support for optimization of the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in for
Python2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python2: Added support for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; iterable constant values,
pre-building those constants ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3: Added support and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; iterable constant values,
pre-building those constants ahead of time. This brings optimization
support for Python3 ranges to what was available for Python2 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Avoid having a special node variange for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; with no arguments,
but create the exception raising node directly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specialized constant value nodes are using less generic
implementations to query e.g. their length or iteration capabilities,
which should speed up many checks on them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added support for the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python3: Added support for the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ascii&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="organisational"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organisational&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The movement to pure C got the final big push. All C++ only idoms of
C++ were removed, and everything works with C11 compilers. A C++03
compiler can be used as a fallback, in case of MSVC or too old gcc
for instance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using pure C, MinGW64 6x is now working properly. The latest version
had problems with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;hypot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; related changes in the C++ standard
library. Using C11 solves that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release also prepares Python 3.6 support, it includes full
language support on the level of CPython 3.6.0b1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The CPython 3.6 test suite was run with Python 3.5 to ensure bug
level compatibility, and had a few findings of incompatibilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="cleanups"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cleanups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last holdouts of classes in Nuitka were removed, and many idioms
of C++ were stopped using.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moved range related helper functions to a dedicated include file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;bytes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to detect Python3 &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; handling or
actual &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bytes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; type existence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trace collections were using a mix-in that was merged with the base
class that every user of it was having.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="tests"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added more static optimization tests, a lot more has become feasible
to decide at run time, and is now done. These are to detect
regressions in that domain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The CPython 3.6 test suite is now also run with CPython 3.5 which
found some incompatibilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release marks a huge step forward. We are having the structure for
type inference now. This will expand in coming releases to cover more
cases, and there are many low hanging fruits for optimization.
Specialized codes for variable versions of certain known shapes seems
feasible now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is also the move towards pure C. This will make the backend
compilation lighter, but due to using C11, we will not suffer any loss
of convenience compared to “C-ish”. The plan is to use continue to use
C++ for compilation for compilers not capable of supporting C11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of static analysis done in Nuitka is now going to quickly
expand, with more and more constructs predicted to raise errors or
simplified. This will be an ongoing activity, as many types of
expressions need to be enhanced, and only one missing will not let it
optimize as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it seems about time to add dedicated code for specific types to be
as fast as C code. This opens up vast possibilities for acceleration and
will lead us to zero overhead C bindings eventually. But initially the
drive is towards enhanced &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; analysis, to become able to know
the precide module expected to be imported, and derive type information
from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coming work will attack to start whole program optimization, as well
as enhanced local value shape analysis, as well specialized type code
generation, which will make Nuitka improve speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0523.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-10-03T16:55:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0524.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Release 0.5.24</title>
    <updated>2016-11-15T09:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-release-0-5-24"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to inform you about the new stable release of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/download.html"&gt;“download now”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release is again focusing on optimization, this time very heavily
on the generator performance, which was found to be much slower than
CPython for some cases. Also there is the usual compatibility work and
improvements for Pure C support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-fixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: The 3.5.2 coroutine new protocol implementation was using
the wrapper from CPython, but it’s not part of the ABI on Windows.
Have our own instead. Fixed in 0.5.23.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windows: Fixed second compilation with MSVC failing. The files
renamed to be C++ files already existed, crashing the compilation.
Fixed in 0.5.23.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mac OS: Fixed creating extension modules with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;.so&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; suffix. This is
now properly determined by looking at the importer details, leading
to correct suffix on all platforms. Fixed in 0.5.23.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Debian: Don’t depend on a C++ compiler primarily anymore, the C
compiler from GNU or clang will do too. Fixed in 0.5.23.1 already.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pure C: Adapted scons compiler detecting to properly consider C11
compilers from the environment, and more gracefully report things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python2: Generators were saving and restoring exceptions, updating
the variables &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sys.exc_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for every context switch, making it
really slow, as these are 3 dictionary updates, normally not needed.
Now it’s only doing it if it means a change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sped up creating generators, coroutines and coroutines by attaching
the closure variable storage directly to the object, using one
variable size allocation, instead of two, once of which was a
standard &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This makes creating them easier and avoids
maintaining the closure pointer entirely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using dedicated compiled cell implementation similar to
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PyCellObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; but fully under our control. This allowed for
smaller code generated, while still giving a slight performance
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added free list implementation to cache generator, coroutines, and
function objects, avoiding the need to create and delete this kind of
objects in a loop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added support for the built-in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, making slight optimizations
to be much faster when iterating over lists and tuples, as well as
fast &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; sum for Python2, and much faster &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; sums too.
This is using a prototype version of a “qiter” concept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provide type shape for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;xrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; calls that are not constant too,
allowing for better optimization related to those.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="tests"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added workarounds for locks being held by Virus Scanners on Windows
to our test runner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enhanced constructs that test generator expressions to more clearly
show the actual construct cost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added construct tests for the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in on various types of
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; containers, making sure we can do all of those really fast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This release improves very heavily on generators in Nuitka. The memory
allocator is used more cleverly, and free lists all around save a lot of
interactions with it. More work lies ahead in this field, as these are
not yet as fast as they should be. However, at least Nuitka should be
faster than CPython for these kind of usages now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, proper pure C in the Scons is relatively important to cover more
of the rarer use cases, where the C compiler is too old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important part is actually how &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; optimization is staging
a new kind of approach for code generation. This could become the
standard code for iterators in loops eventually, making &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; loops
even faster. This will be for future releases to expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-release-0524.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This is to inform you about the new stable release of Nuitka. It is the extremely compatible Python compiler,
“download now”.</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <published>2016-11-15T09:43:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
