<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posts tagged presentation</title>
  <updated>2022-02-13T03:14:06.605576+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/tag/presentation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka---pycon-de-video.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka - PyCON DE Video</title>
    <updated>2011-10-22T06:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-pycon-de-video"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello everybody,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Video of my presentation is online:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pyvideo.org/pycon-de-2011/nuitka-der-python-compiler.html"&gt;https://pyvideo.org/pycon-de-2011/nuitka-der-python-compiler.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving it to Mike Müller to announce here the links to everything, when
it’s all finished. Thanks for the good work, the video was very well
done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition-update admonition"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Update&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is also available via Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EYByCjptbhY" style="border: 0; height: 430px; width: 600px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Yours,&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Kay&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka---pycon-de-video.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Hello everybody,</summary>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="git" label="git"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="presentation" label="presentation"/>
    <category term="video" label="video"/>
    <published>2011-10-22T06:39:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html</id>
    <title>My Europython 2013 report</title>
    <updated>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="my-europython-2013-report"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;Python compiler Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BDjXZY_8d58" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk went really well. I believe one can clearly see that I felt
really good and at ease. The state presented is very good and progress -
there was a lot, so that was great. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2013.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of the talk may also be
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it definitely raised a lot of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last years talk is also there. You can (maybe) see that I was 20kg more
weight then, and also &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more excited, at least initially.
Background: I was surprised then that Guido van Rossum was attending the
talk, plus I was kind of not in the state of this year, the confidence
that people should believe, that things will work after that, was not
yet there. I knew it, but standing in front of a croud and saying, look
I am attempting what you consider impossible, or even have failed at, is
not easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZDHkla5rllg" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2012.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of that talk which may
also be interesting, but of course are outdated somewhat now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="years-make-differences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Years make differences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, the progress happened since 2012 made a difference. Nuitka has
proven things. Let’s see what this year does to it. I would hope for
real type inference optimization and portable mode to be there next
year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider that is the a &lt;em&gt;spare time effort&lt;/em&gt;. Lots of people lauded it for
the out of the box experience, and how it just works. That’s right. I
put a lot of focus on stability, correctness, and ease of use. In fact,
since my return, I have mostly worked on the feedback I got in that
domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the relatively small amount of time I can invest (outside of
holidays), it’s make very fast progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="out-of-the-box-thinking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Out of the box thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback during the conference was great. While Nuitka is not yet
seeing a lot of users, and not as many contributions or donations as I
would hope for, but that’s kind of expected with my out of the box
thinking there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few people at Europython really need a Python compiler. The most
important exception are scientific people, doing number crunching. And I
made some interesting contacts there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my return, I have been receiving a bunch of bug reports. Some of
which were unfortunately regressions of 0.4.4, and these got fixed in
two hotfix releases. Currently 0.4.4.2 is released, and contains a huge
amount of fixes, mostly stuff found by the surge new users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I deserved that, having said that I didn’t have to do hotfixes for a
while now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="florence"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Florence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a lovely place, and so lovely people. It’s a tourist place, true,
but it’s very open minded. The food is extremely good. And going from
the conference hotel straight over to the river to meet up and have a
few beers was very comfortable for after-conference stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have been there 2 times, and the conference even 3 times,
it’s moving on, to Berlin, which I sort of regret. Knowing the place
somewhat definitely is an advantage by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-revolution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that came to my mind during the conference, witnessing the
large amount of non-satisfaction, was that the community is fed up with
the leadership. Questioned about lack of Python3 adoption, a PSF guy in
his presentation said they were 3 years into a 5 years plan, and got
interrupted by laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be about time, somebody actually gets up, removes the GIL and has
a Python2.8 that is compatible. Obviously that’s much more useful. It
could be a Python3.x with compatibility names of modules, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
statement, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict.iteritems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; added, probably also making some of
the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mess more harmless, and providing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering that I have in fact been playing with the idea of forking
CPython top versions, to add things, that would allow Nuitka to work
better with it, that could be a staging ground, where such changes are
nurtured. On the other hand, Nuitka is too irrelevant yet to drive this,
and it would detract me away from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="gains"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Nuitka got a lot more exposure. And one guy watching the talk even
created a really &lt;a class="reference external" href="/_static/Nuitka-Logo-Symbol.svg"&gt;nice logo&lt;/a&gt; for
it. I will make it a separate announcement though, and the next release
is going to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the aftermath, there were much bug useful reports. And new ideas.
And reinforcement that what I am doing is actually useful to some people
already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Donations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My travel to Florence was in part funded by donations. Thanks a lot to
all of you who have given, and who would like to also &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;make a donation&lt;/a&gt;. Should I receive sufficient donations, I
intend to go to FOSDEM 2014 as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to Berlin will be a bit cheaper this time around, as I can travel
there via train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Europython 2012 and 2013 both are among the times of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my Python compiler Nuitka.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <category term="presentation" label="presentation"/>
    <category term="video" label="video"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
