<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posts tagged conference</title>
  <updated>2022-02-13T04:46:00.223973+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/tag/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/pycon-de-2011-my-report.html</id>
    <title>PyCON DE 2011 - My Report</title>
    <updated>2011-10-08T21:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="pycon-de-2011-my-report"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PyCON DE 2011 is just over, sprints are still happening over the
weekend, but my wife wouldn’t allow me to stay away for that long, so
it’s not for me this time. Maybe next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I feel very happy and excited that I went there. What a
&lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt; experience this was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first German PyCON and clearly it was overdue as it was now
the merger of many already grown up communities. A huge number of talks
over 3 days in 3 parallel tracks, with 3 keynotes, was an outstanding
program. And very well run. Strict time management, every detail was
well prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can only admire the professional preparation and setup. I wanted to
say thank you deeply. I didn’t consider it possible to be this good.
Clearly not a first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the talks, most often in the technical track, but other tracks
would have been very interesting too. The parallelism was making me do
hard decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="food"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The food was great too. I esp. liked the Asian day, but there was also
Italian and French, and what many liked very much is that there was a
Vegan food offer too. I do not live vegan style, but I appreciate good
food and the vegan food often is that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="social-event"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Social Event&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social event was a visit to a “Variete” (music hall, French origin),
where I am sure, there will be images posted, I currently &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/onyame/6222954609/in/pool-1775853&amp;#64;N21/"&gt;found this
one&lt;/a&gt;
, that my wife will find interesting too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="leipzig"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leipzig&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of the organization team, the city “Leipzig”, where we also
got to have a guided city tour of fantastic enthusiasms, was very high.
I knew Leipzig from earlier visits and liked it before, but this time it
seemed everybody was even friendlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="site"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The convention place “Kubus” was very well chosen, absolutely ideal.
It’s got good equipment, and that large room setup, where you can make a
split with movable walls, and have 3 big screens. The acoustics were
pretty damn good there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="my-own-presentation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My own Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As to my own presentation, it was well received, although I sort of
regret that I agreed to have only 30m instead of original plan of 60m. I
had so much to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up with getting my manifesto part out, but that one pretty well.
And it’s OK I guess, because nobody really listens that long anyway. And
my major points came across that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That focus on my Nuitka “manifesto” was probably a good idea. The talk
will be available online as a video, I will link it then. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-DE-2011.pdf"&gt;PDF that
I presented only a small part of&lt;/a&gt;, is linked here. I believe
it went pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will use that content from the PDF in updated documentation (currently
ongoing in PDF is work to use REST and document a lot more). The
presentation was created with “rst2pdf”, which I find is a fantastic
tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="contacts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contacts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="cython-lxml"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cython / lxml&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then contacts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on I already made contacts with interesting people, e.g. with
Dr.Stefan Behnel, author of lxml and core Cython developer. I him
offered a beer for using his software in the best of Free Software
traditions. He doesn’t drink these, but a large mango juice counts too
or so I assume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also talked about Cython and Nuitka, and the common history we had as
well. For some time, I attempted to change Cython, but that failed to
get the developers support at the time. Not wanting to deviate from
PyRex clearly isn’t the state anymore, but that was then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had a evening session of showing each other the good and bad
parts, comparing was quite fun. And it was quite interesting to the both
of us. I believe we made friends and will only benefit another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed my goals, and I think we came to the conclusion that they
are in fact different enough from Cythons. Although I go away with the
sense, that of course Stefan believes, it would be better if I joined
Cython. Naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s not going to happen. I think i have a cleaner and better
implementation now, closer to my goals with a realistic chance to
succeed. To me it would be a step back to fix language parsing issues
and incompatibilities of Cython, with the danger that my goals will not
be shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of these things, I would mention function call errors,
where e.g. Cython gives different and sometimes worse error messages
than CPython, and I designed the code so that it does things in that
same order than CPython does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It do not want to give different error messages, and who knows, somebody
may check for the exception text and expect CPython output. In this
case, I will rather accept a worse performance, than an incompatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminating function parameter parsing for the whole program as far as
possible is going to be more worthwhile anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in my mind, Cython is something I can and do recommend. For as long
as I am not able to declare Nuitka “useful” yet. That statement may come
within a year though. In my mind, in many fields Nuitka is already
superior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pyhasse"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyHasse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting contact I made, was with the author of PyHasse. It’s
Rainer Bruggemann, who is a really nice and witty guy. He introduced me
to how he applies graph theory to multi-parameter optimization problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We agreed that we will try and work together on this project. Hopefully
it will come to pass. One thing I personally wanted, was to get into
contact with people who understand or are part of the scientific
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can see what NumPy is. But I may never know myself what it really is,
unless I find proxies, and make these kind of contacts. The same thing
is true of Django, or e.g. Mercurial. I am positive though that with
time, and such conferences, my knowledge of these will only grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We said that we will try and see how far we can go. In the worst case,
Nuitka will not yet be useful, but I will have a clearer image what is
needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="debian"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Debian&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw the presentation from Jan Dittberner and met him later too, asking
him questions, and generally discussing Debian packaging of Nuitka. He
encouraged me to contact the Debian Python Team, and so I will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the chance to make contact with a Debian guy, who made a
presentation on how to package Python modules for Debian. He gave me
hints on how to solve that “find files near me” issue that plagues
Nuitka just as much as other software. Really kind and helpful guy and
clearly I admire Debian Developers, keep up the good work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="general"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;General&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made contacts with lots of other people. Python is diverse and it
was fun to get to know, many people with similar and entirely different
backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mood was extremely constructive. Nuitka was well received, but
that’s not why I say it. There is that general sense of respect around
that German community, you can feel how pretty much everybody is well
established and doesn’t have to disprove the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="keynotes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One keynotes speaker had a part about how trolling and hate is bad for a
community, but that’s not the German Python community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another keynote speaker (Paul Everitt) had a part about how Zope, which
was kind of his project, failed in many ways. He seemed to be quite
disappointed about that, which triggered me to point out, that he should
start his story with Apache, and not see the “failure to integrate” as a
failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there had not been Apache failing, there wouldn’t have been Zope, and
then not Django, etc. that’s kind of normal and actually good. He agreed
and pointed out how Apache was created from another project that had
failed to integrate people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You either fork a projects code, or ideas. The fork still should credit
and appreciate the predecessor/origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, Cython failed to integrate me. Which triggered me to come up
with Nuitka, and as I will point out over time (there ought to be
postings and there probably will be), some better approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So not integrating me is not necessarily a failure. If it were not for
Cython, there would not be Nuitka. The original projects will regret the
fork/remake, but they probably shouldn’t. Competition is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="lets-repeat-that"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lets repeat that&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the PyCON DE 2011 was a huge success. I will most likely go
again to update people on Nuitka. It’s already clear there will be a
PyCON DE 2012 I understand. And I am aiming for a slot at PyCON EU 2012
next year too. I wanted to go in 2011, but need to not put it in my
early booked holiday again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you know what Murphy says about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Yours,&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Kay Hayen&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/pycon-de-2011-my-report.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>The PyCON DE 2011 is just over, sprints are still happening over the
weekend, but my wife wouldn’t allow me to stay away for that long, so
it’s not for me this time. Maybe next time.</summary>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <published>2011-10-08T21:24:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html</id>
    <title>My Europython 2013 report</title>
    <updated>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="my-europython-2013-report"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;Python compiler Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BDjXZY_8d58" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk went really well. I believe one can clearly see that I felt
really good and at ease. The state presented is very good and progress -
there was a lot, so that was great. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2013.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of the talk may also be
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it definitely raised a lot of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last years talk is also there. You can (maybe) see that I was 20kg more
weight then, and also &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more excited, at least initially.
Background: I was surprised then that Guido van Rossum was attending the
talk, plus I was kind of not in the state of this year, the confidence
that people should believe, that things will work after that, was not
yet there. I knew it, but standing in front of a croud and saying, look
I am attempting what you consider impossible, or even have failed at, is
not easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZDHkla5rllg" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2012.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of that talk which may
also be interesting, but of course are outdated somewhat now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="years-make-differences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Years make differences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, the progress happened since 2012 made a difference. Nuitka has
proven things. Let’s see what this year does to it. I would hope for
real type inference optimization and portable mode to be there next
year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider that is the a &lt;em&gt;spare time effort&lt;/em&gt;. Lots of people lauded it for
the out of the box experience, and how it just works. That’s right. I
put a lot of focus on stability, correctness, and ease of use. In fact,
since my return, I have mostly worked on the feedback I got in that
domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the relatively small amount of time I can invest (outside of
holidays), it’s make very fast progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="out-of-the-box-thinking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Out of the box thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback during the conference was great. While Nuitka is not yet
seeing a lot of users, and not as many contributions or donations as I
would hope for, but that’s kind of expected with my out of the box
thinking there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few people at Europython really need a Python compiler. The most
important exception are scientific people, doing number crunching. And I
made some interesting contacts there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my return, I have been receiving a bunch of bug reports. Some of
which were unfortunately regressions of 0.4.4, and these got fixed in
two hotfix releases. Currently 0.4.4.2 is released, and contains a huge
amount of fixes, mostly stuff found by the surge new users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I deserved that, having said that I didn’t have to do hotfixes for a
while now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="florence"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Florence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a lovely place, and so lovely people. It’s a tourist place, true,
but it’s very open minded. The food is extremely good. And going from
the conference hotel straight over to the river to meet up and have a
few beers was very comfortable for after-conference stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have been there 2 times, and the conference even 3 times,
it’s moving on, to Berlin, which I sort of regret. Knowing the place
somewhat definitely is an advantage by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-revolution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that came to my mind during the conference, witnessing the
large amount of non-satisfaction, was that the community is fed up with
the leadership. Questioned about lack of Python3 adoption, a PSF guy in
his presentation said they were 3 years into a 5 years plan, and got
interrupted by laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be about time, somebody actually gets up, removes the GIL and has
a Python2.8 that is compatible. Obviously that’s much more useful. It
could be a Python3.x with compatibility names of modules, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
statement, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict.iteritems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; added, probably also making some of
the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mess more harmless, and providing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering that I have in fact been playing with the idea of forking
CPython top versions, to add things, that would allow Nuitka to work
better with it, that could be a staging ground, where such changes are
nurtured. On the other hand, Nuitka is too irrelevant yet to drive this,
and it would detract me away from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="gains"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Nuitka got a lot more exposure. And one guy watching the talk even
created a really &lt;a class="reference external" href="/_static/Nuitka-Logo-Symbol.svg"&gt;nice logo&lt;/a&gt; for
it. I will make it a separate announcement though, and the next release
is going to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the aftermath, there were much bug useful reports. And new ideas.
And reinforcement that what I am doing is actually useful to some people
already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Donations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My travel to Florence was in part funded by donations. Thanks a lot to
all of you who have given, and who would like to also &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;make a donation&lt;/a&gt;. Should I receive sufficient donations, I
intend to go to FOSDEM 2014 as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to Berlin will be a bit cheaper this time around, as I can travel
there via train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Europython 2012 and 2013 both are among the times of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my Python compiler Nuitka.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <category term="presentation" label="presentation"/>
    <category term="video" label="video"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/not-going-to-fosdem-2014.html</id>
    <title>Not going to FOSDEM 2014</title>
    <updated>2014-01-18T20:48:53+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="not-going-to-fosdem-2014"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I submitted a talk for FOSDEM “Python has a compiler now”. And it
didn’t get accepted. Quite a surprise to me, but likely mostly logical.
These are the accepted talks (link since became unavailable) and well,
it surely didn’t fit in, right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intent was to introduce &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt; to the
larger community. Not going to happen now, but maybe next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly triggered by the rejection, I am questioning Europython 2014 in
Berlin as a useful destination too. To me it seems, that code writing is
the best way to create the community at this time anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/not-going-to-fosdem-2014.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>So I submitted a talk for FOSDEM “Python has a compiler now”. And it
didn’t get accepted. Quite a surprise to me, but likely mostly logical.
These are the accepted talks (link since became unavailable) and well,
it surely didn’t fit in, right.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <published>2014-01-18T20:48:53+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
