<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posts tagged NTW</title>
  <updated>2022-02-15T15:31:36.388367+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/tag/ntw/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-1.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #1</title>
    <updated>2018-07-27T07:08:54+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-1"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-1" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka this week #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#new-series-rationale" id="id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#planned-mode" id="id3"&gt;Planned Mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#locals-dict" id="id4"&gt;Locals Dict&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nodes-need-finalization" id="id5"&gt;Nodes need Finalization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#impact-on-memory-usage" id="id6"&gt;Impact on Memory Usage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#type-hints-question" id="id7"&gt;Type Hints Question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#python-3-7" id="id8"&gt;Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#coroutine-compatibility" id="id9"&gt;Coroutine Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#pylint-troubles" id="id10"&gt;PyLint Troubles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#todo-solving" id="id11"&gt;TODO solving&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#issues-encountered" id="id12"&gt;Issues Encountered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id13"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="new-series-rationale"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I tend to prefer coding over communication too much. I think I
need to make more transparent what I am doing. Also things, will be
getting exciting continuously for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to status report posts, many years ago, every 3 months or so, and
that was nice for me also to get an idea of what changed, but I stopped.
What did not happen, was to successfully engage other people to
contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I am getting more intense. I will aim to do roughly weekly or
bi-weekly reports, where I highlight things that are going on, newly
found issues, hotfixes, all the things Nuitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="planned-mode"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Planned Mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will do it this fashion. I will write a post to the mailing list,
right about wednesday every week or so. I need to pick a day. I am
working from home that day, saving me commute time. I will invest that
time into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing will not be too high quality at times. Bare with me there.
Then I will check feedback from the list, if any. Hope is for it to
point out the things where I am not correct, missing, or even engage
right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topics are going to be random, albeit repeating. I will try and make
links to previous issues where applicable. Therefore also the TOC, which
makes for link targets in the pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="locals-dict"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Locals Dict&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am speaking of locals dict, I am talking of class scopes (and
functions with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; statements). These started to use actual
dictionary a while ago, which was a severe setback to optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, so for this week, after a first prototype was making the
replacement of local dict assignment and references for Python2, and
kind of worked through my buildbots, flawlessly, I immediately noticed
that it would require some refactoring to not depend on the locals
scopes to be only in one of the trace collections. Thinking of future
inlining, maybe part of a locals scope was going to be in multiple
functions, that ought to not be affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore I made a global registry of locals scopes, and working on
those, I checked its variables, if they can be forward propagated, and
do this not per module, but after all the modules have been done. This
is kind of a setback for the idea of module specific optimization
(cacheable later on) vs. program optimization, but since that is not yet
a thing, it can remain this way for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I did that, I was interested to see the effect, but to my horror, I
noticed, that memory was not released for the locals dict nodes. It was
way too involved with cyclic dependencies, which are bad. So that was
problematic of course. Compilation to keep nodes in memory for both
tracing the usage as a locals dict and temporary variables, wasn’t going
to help scaling at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution is finalization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="nodes-need-finalization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Nodes need Finalization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So replaced nodes reference a parent, and then the locals scope
references variables, and trace collections referencing variables, which
reference locals scopes, and accesses referencing traces, and so on. The
garbage collector can handle some of this, but seems I was getting past
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a solution, I started to add a finalize method, which released the
links for locals scopes, when they are fully propagated, on the next
run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding a finalize to all nodes, ought to make sure, memory is released
soon, and might even find bugs, as nodes become unusable after they are
supposedly unused. Obviously, there will currently be cases, where nodes
becomes unused, but they are not finalized yet. Also, often this is more
manual, because part of the node is to be released, but one child is
re-used. That is messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="impact-on-memory-usage"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Impact on Memory Usage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result was a bit disappointing. Yes, memory usage of mercurial
compilation went back again, but mostly to what it had been. Some
classes are now having their locals dict forward propagated, but the
effect is not always a single dictionary making yet. Right now, function
definitions, are not forward at all propagated. This is a task I want to
take on before next release though, but maybe not, there is other things
too. But I am assuming that will make most class dictionaries created
without using any variables at all anymore, which should make it really
lean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="type-hints-question"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Type Hints Question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, asking about type hints, I got the usual question about Nuitka
going to use it. And my stance is unchanged. They are just hints, not
reliable. Need to behave the same if users do it wrong. Suggested to
create decorated which make type hints enforced. But I expect nobody
takes this on though. I need to make it a Github issue of Nuitka,
although technically it is pure CPython work and ought to be done
independently. Right now Nuitka is not yet there anyway yet, to take
full advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-3-7"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, for Python 3.7, I have long gotten the 3.6 test suite to pass. I
raised 2 bugs with CPython, one of which lead to update of a failing
test. Nuitka had with large delay, caught of with what &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__annotations__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; was doing in a class. Only with the recent work for
proper locals dict code generation, we could enforce a name to be local,
and have proper code generation, that allows for it to be unset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was of course a bit of work. But the optimization behind was always
kind of necessary to get right. But now, that I got this, think of my
amazement when for 3.7 they reverted to the old behavior, where
annotiatons then corrupt the module annotations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other bug is a reference counting bug, where Nuitka tests were
failing with CPython 3.7, and turns out, there is a bug in the
dictionary implementation of 3.7, but it only corrupts counts reported,
not actual objects, so it’s harmless, but means for 3.7.0 the reference
count tests are disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working through the 3.7 suite, I am cherry picking commits, that e.g.
allow the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;repr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; of compiled functions to contain &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;&amp;lt;compiled_function&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;...&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and the like. Nothing huge yet. There is now a subscript of type,
and foremost the async syntax became way more liberal, so it is more
complex for Nuitka to make out if it is a coroutine due to something
happening inside a generator declared inside of it. Also &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;cr_origin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
was added to coroutines, but that is mostly it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="coroutine-compatibility"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Coroutine Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bigger thing was that I debugged coroutines and their interaction with
uncompiled and compiled coroutines awaiting one another, and turns out,
there was a lot to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next release will be much better compatible with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;asyncio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module
and its futures, esp with exceptions to cancel tasks passed along. That
required to clone a lot of CPython generator code, due to how ugly they
mess with bytecode instruction pointers in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; on an
uncompiled coroutine, as they don’t work with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; method unlike
everything else has to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pylint-troubles"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;PyLint Troubles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For PyLint, the 2.0.0 release found new things, but unfortunately for
2.0.1 there is a lot of regressions that I had to report. I fixed the
versions of first PyLint, and now also Astroid, so Travis cannot
suddenly start to fail due to a PyLint release finding new warnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, if you make a PR on Github, a PyLint update will break it.
And also the cron job on Travis that checks master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As somebody pointed out, I am now using &lt;cite&gt;requires.io
&amp;lt;https://requires.io/github/kayhayen/Nuitka/requirements/?branch=factory&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
to check for Nuitka dependencies. But since 1.9.2 is still needed for
Python2, that kind of is bound to give alarms for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="todo-solving"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;TODO solving&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of doing off tasks, when I am with my notebook in some
place, and don’t know what to work on. So I have some 2 hours recently
like this, and used it to look at &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;TODO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and resolve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a bunch of cleanups for static code helpers. There was one in my
mind about calling a function with a single argument. That fast call
required a local array with one element to put the arg into. That makes
using code ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="issues-encountered"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Issues Encountered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module of Python3 hates compiled classes and their
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; around &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Since it manually unwraps
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and then calls it itself, it then finds that a
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; object cannot be called. It’s purpose is to sit in the
class dictionary to give a descriptor that removes the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; arg from
the call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am contemplating submitting an upstream patch for CPython here. The
hard coded check for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PyFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; on the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; value is hard to
emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am putting the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; into the dictionary passed already.
But the undecorated function should be there for full compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to make compiled function type that is both a staticmethod
alike and a function, maybe I can work around it. But it’s ugly and a
burden. But it would need no change. And maybe there is more core
wanting to call &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; manually&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intend to make a release, probably this weekend. It might not contain
full 3.7 compatibility yet, although I am aiming at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I want to turn to “goto generators”, a scalability improvement of
generators and coroutines that I will talk about next week then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-1.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #1</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-07-27T07:08:54+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-2.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #2</title>
    <updated>2018-08-02T07:08:54+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-2"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-2" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka this week #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#new-series-rationale" id="id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#python-3-7" id="id3"&gt;Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#msi-3-7-files-for-nuitka" id="id4"&gt;MSI 3.7 files for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#planned-mode" id="id5"&gt;Planned Mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id6"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#python3-enumerators" id="id7"&gt;Python3 Enumerators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id8"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id9"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="new-series-rationale"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As discussed last week in &lt;a class="reference external" href="./nuitka-this-week-1.html"&gt;TWN #1&lt;/a&gt; this is
a new series that I am using to highlight things that are going on,
newly found issues, hotfixes, all the things Nuitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-3-7"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the first release with official 3.7 support, huge milestone in
terms of catching up. Generic classes posed a few puzzles, and need more
refinements for error handling, but good code works now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class creation got a bit more complex, yet again, which will make it
even hard to know the exact base classes to be used. But eventually we
will manage to overcome this and statically optimize that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="msi-3-7-files-for-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;MSI 3.7 files for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building the MSI files for Nuitka ran into a 3.7.0 regression of CPython
failing to build them, that I reported and seems to be valid bug of
theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So they will be missing for some longer time. Actually I wasn’t so sure
if they are all that useful, or working as expected for the runners, but
with the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mode of execution, that ought to be a non-issue.
so it would be nice to keep them for those who use them for deployment
internally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="planned-mode"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Planned Mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a change here. This is going to be a draft post until I publish
it, so I might the link, or mention it on the list, but I do not think I
will wait for feedback, where there is not going to be all that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am shooting this off the web site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an exciting field of work, that I have been busy with this week.
I will briefly describe the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So generators in Python are more generally called coroutines in other
places, and basically that is code shaking hands, executing resuming in
one, handing back a piece of data back and forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, the way of doing this is &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and more recently &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; as a convienant way for of doing it in a loop in Python3. I still
recall the days when that was a statement. Then communication was one
way only. Actually when I was still privately doing Nuitka based on then
Python 2.5 and was then puzzled for Python 2.6, when I learned in Nuitka
about it becoming an expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way this is implemented in Python, is that execution of a frame is
simply suspended, and another frame stack bytecode is activated. This
switching is of course very fast potentially, the state is already fully
preserved on the stack of the virtual machine, which is owned by the
frame. For Nuitka, when it still was C++, it wasn’t going to be possible
to interrupt execution without preserving the stack. So what I did was
very similar, and I started to use &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;makecontext/setcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to
implement what I call fibers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically that is C level stack switching, but with a huge issue. Python
does not grow stacks, but can need a lot of stack space below. Therefore
1MB or even 2MB per generator was allocated, to be able to make deep
function calls if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So using a lot of generators on 32 bits could easily hit a 2GB limit.
And now with Python3.5 coroutines people use more and more of them, and
hit memory issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, goto generators, now that C is possible, are an entirely new
solution. With it, Nuitka will use one stack only. Generator code will
become re-entrant, store values between entries on the heap, and
continue execution at goto destinations dispatched by a switch according
to last exit of the generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am now making changes to cleanup the way variable declarations and
accesses for the C variables are being made. More on that next week
though. For now I am very exited about the many cleanups that stem from
it. The code generation used to have many special bells and whistles,
and they were generalized into one thing now, making for cleaner and
easier to understand Nuitka code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python3-enumerators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Python3 Enumerators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On interesting thing, is that an incompatibility related to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
will go away now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The automatic &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; that we had to hack into it, because the
Python core will do it for uncompiled functions only, had to be done
while declaring the class. So it was visible and causing issues with at
least the Python enum module, which wants to call your &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
manually. Because why would it not?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But turns out, for Python3 the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is not needed anymore.
So this is now only done for Python2, where it is needed, and things
work smoothly with this kind of code now too. This is currently in my
factory testing and will probably become part of a hotfix if it turns
out good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately after the release, some rarely run test, where I compiled
all the code on my machine, found 2 older bugs, obscure ones arguably,
that I made into a hotfix, also because the test runner was having a
regression with 3.7, which prevented some package builds. So that was
0.5.32.1 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I received a bug report about &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;await&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; where a self test of
Nuitka fails and reports an optimization error. Very nice, the new
exceptions that automatically dump involved nodes as XML made it
immediately clear from the report, what is going on, even without having
to reproduce anything. I bundled a 3.7 improvement for error cases in
class creation with it. So that was the 0.5.32.2 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing goto generators is my top priority, but I am also going over
minor issues with the 3.7 test suite, fixing test cases there, and as
with e.g. the enum issue, even known issues this now finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-2.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #2</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-08-02T07:08:54+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-3.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #3</title>
    <updated>2018-08-11T11:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-3"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-3" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka this week #3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#new-series-rationale" id="id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id3"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id4"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id5"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id6"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="new-series-rationale"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;New Series Rationale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is working out well so far. I think driving more attention at the
things that are going on can only be good. Also to explain will always
help. It also kind of motivates me a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also as part of my communications offensive, I am using my Twitter
account more regularly. I used to highlight important fixes, or
occasionally releases of some importance there. I will continue to do
only important stuff there, but with more regularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I noticed in the past, even when I do not post, followers makes me
happy. So here you go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This continues &lt;a class="reference external" href="./nuitka-this-week-2.html#goto-generators"&gt;TWN #2&lt;/a&gt;
where I promised to speak more of it, and this is the main focus of my
work on Nuitka right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brief summary, context switches were how this was initially implemented.
The main reason being that for C++ there never was going to be a way to
save and restore state in the middle of an expression that involves
constructors and destructors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward some years, and C-ish entered the picture. No objects are
used anymore, and Nuitka is purely C11 now, which has convenience of
C++, but no objects. Instead &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;goto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is used a lot already. So every
time an exception occurs, a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;goto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is done, every time a branch is
done, a loop exit or continue, you get it, another &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;goto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But so far, all Python level variables of a frame live on that C stack
still, and the context switch is done with functions that swap stack.
That is fast, but the imporant drawback is that it takes more memory.
How deep of a stack will we need? And we can use really many, if you
imagine a pool of 1000 coroutines, that quickly become impossible to
deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the new way of doing this basically goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was some far becoming something along this lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-c notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;impl_g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;NuitkaGenerator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;YIELD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;const_int_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;YIELD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;const_int_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyErr_SetException&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;StopIteration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;YIELD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in there was basically doing the switching of the stacks
and for the C code, it looked like a normal function call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new approach, this is done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-c notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;impl_g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;NuitkaGenerator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;switch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m_resume_point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;goto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;resume_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;goto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;resume_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m_yielded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;const_int_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;resume_point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;resume_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m_yielded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;const_int_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;generator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;resume_point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;resume_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyErr_SetException&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;StopIteration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the function has an initial dispatcher. Resume point 0
means we are starting at the top. Then every &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; results in a
function return with an updated resume point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I experimented with this actually a long time ago, and experimental code
was the result that remained in Nuitka. The problem left to solve was to
store the variables that would normally live on the stack, in a heap
storage. That is what I am currently working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads me to “heap storage”, which is what I am currently working on
and will report on next week. Once that is there, goto generators can
work, and will become the norm. Until then, I am refactoring a lot to
get accesses to variable go through proper objects that know their
storage locations and types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there have been 2 more hotfixes. One was to make the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__new__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; compatibility available that I talked about last week in
&lt;cite&gt;TWN #2 &amp;lt;./nuitka-this-week-2.html#python3-enumerators&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; coupled with a
new minor things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then another one, actually important, where Python3
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__annotations__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; by default was the empty dictionary, but then could
be modified, corrupting the Nuitka internally used one severely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I have on factory another fix for nested namespace packages in
Python3 and that might become another hotfix soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, I am following the git flow model, where it’s easy to push
out small fixes, and just those, on top of the last release. I tend to
decide based on importance. However, I feel that with the important
fixes in the hotfixes now, it’s probably time to make a full release, to
be sure everybody gets those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing heap storage is my top priority right now and I hope to
complete the refactorings necessary in the coming week. I will also talk
about how it also enables C types work next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next week then!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-3.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #3</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-08-11T11:58:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-4.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #4</title>
    <updated>2018-08-17T14:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-4"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-4" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka this week #4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id2"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#tox-plugin" id="id3"&gt;Tox Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id4"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id5"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id6"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This continues &lt;a class="reference external" href="./nuitka-this-week-3.html#goto-generators"&gt;TWN #3&lt;/a&gt;
where I explained what is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good news is, at the time Python2 generators were largely working with
the new ways, in the mean time not only did all of the Python 2.7 test
suite pass with goto generators, also did the Python 3.4 test suite,
i.e. also the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is working with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it was done is to set &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;m_yieldfrom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in generators, and then to
enter a state, where the code will only be resumed, when that
sub-generator that currently it is yielding from, is finished. That
makes it very much like normal yield. In fact, code generation is hardly
different there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the whole purpose is to get rid of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;make/get/setcontext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, the
next stop is coroutines. They have &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;async&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;async&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;await&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; but at the end of the day, the implementation comes down to
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; really with only a lot of sugar applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I am debugging “goto coroutines”. It’s hard to tell when it
will be finished, and then &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;asyncgen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; will be waiting still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is easily the largest change in a long time, esp. due to the heap
storage changes that I already discussed. One this is finished, I expect
to turn towards C types with relative ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="tox-plugin"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Tox Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony Shaw took on Tox and Nuitka and created a plugin that allows
using Nuitka. I am still wrapping my head around these things. It’s only
a proof of concept yet. I will give it more coverage in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on twitter if you like, I will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there have even more hotfixes. One addresses memory leaks found with
the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; while I was adding tests. Usually if I encounter an
old issue that has a small fix, that is what I do, push out a hotfix
using the git flow model. Also nested namespace packages for Python3,
those are the ones without a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__init__.py&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; were not working after the
original directory was removed, and that got fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And right now, I have hotfixes for frames &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;close&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; method, which
apparently was never updated to work properly for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;coroutines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;asyncgen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;. That is going to be in the next hotfix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the heap storage seems pretty complete now, and goto generators are
on the final stretch. As always, things feel right around the corner.
But it’s unclear how much longer I will have to debug. I am pretty sure
the bare work of doing asyncgen is going to be low. Debugging that too
then, that is the hard part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new release seems justified, but I kind of do not want to make it
without that major new code used. Because apparently during the
debugging, I tend to find issues that need hotfixes, so I will wait for
the goto generator work to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-4.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #4</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-08-17T14:55:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-5.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #5</title>
    <updated>2018-08-24T12:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-5"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-5" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id3"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks" id="id4"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#holiday" id="id5"&gt;Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#static-compilation" id="id6"&gt;Static Compilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id7"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id8"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#bug-tracker" id="id9"&gt;Bug Tracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#issue-backlog" id="id10"&gt;Issue Backlog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id11"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id12"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finished. Done. Finally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benchmarking was exciting. One program benchmark I had run in the past,
was twice as fast than before, showing that the new implementation is
indeed much faster, which is fantastic news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating generator expressions and using them both got substantially
faster and that is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a fair amount of time to debug coroutines and asyncgen based
on the new goto implementation. But the result is really good, and a
fair amount of old bugs have been fixed. There always had been a
segfault with asyncgen test that now has been eradicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major observation is now, with only one C stack, debugging got a lot
easier before, where context switches left much of the program state not
reachable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posted this one Twitter already:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://speedcenter.nuitka.net/constructs/construct-builtinsumwithgenerator.html"&gt;Nuitka Speedcenter Builtin sum with generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one construct test has been a problem child, where Nuitka was
slower than CPython 2.x, and very little faster than 3.x, and now with
goto generators finally has become consistently faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will explain what you see there in the next issue. The short version
is that there is code, in which for one run, one line is used, and in
another the other line is used, and then the “construct” is measure that
way, by making the delta of the two. That construct performance is then
compared between Python and Nuitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if e.g. Nuitka is already better at looping, that won’t influence the
number of making that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; call with a generator expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative line uses the generator expression, to make sure the
construction time is not counted. To measure that, there is another
construct test, that just creates it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://speedcenter.nuitka.net/constructs/construct-generatorexpressioncreation.html"&gt;Nuitka Speedcenter Generator Expression Creation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one shows that stable Nuitka was already faster at creating them,
but that the develop version got even faster again. As creating
generator objects became more lightweight, that is also news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are constructs for many parts of Python, to shed a light on how
Nuitka fares for that particular one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="holiday"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my 2 weeks holiday, I will try and focus on the next big thing, C
types, something also started in the past, and where recent changes as
part of the heap storage, should make it really a lot easier to get it
finished. In fact I don’t know right now, why my &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; experimental
work shouldn’t just prove to be workable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not going to post a TWN issue next week, mostly because my home
servers won’t be running, and the static site is rendered on one of
them. Of course that would be movable, but I won’t bother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to post a lot on Twitter though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="static-compilation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Static Compilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Github issue where I describe how pyenv on macOS ought to be
possible to use, and indeed, a brave soul has confirmed and even
provided the concrete commands. All it takes now is somebody to fit this
into the existing caching mechanism of Nuitka and to make sure the
static library is properly patched to work with these commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now is anyone of you going to create the code that will solve it for
good?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on twitter if you like, I will post important stuff as it
happens there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there have been yet again more hotfixes. Some are about coroutine
and asyncgen corruptions for closes of frames. Multiprocessing plugin on
Windows will work in all cases now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noteworthy was that the “0.5.32.6” was having a git merge problem on the
cherry-pick that git didn’t tell me about, leading to crashes. That made
it necessary to push an update right after. I was confused that I didn’t
get a conflict, because there was one. But I am to blame for not
checking the actual diff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="bug-tracker"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Bug Tracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next release will make Github the official tracker for Nuitka
issues. I am working down the issues on the old tracker. The web site
already pointed users there for a while, and I was set on this for some
time, but yesterday I focused on taking action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically what won me over is the easier templating of issues and pull
requests that would have been possible with Roundup, but never happened.
Also the OpenID integration that bugs.python.org has, never became
available to me in a ready usable form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="issue-backlog"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Issue Backlog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finishing goto “generators allowed” for around 10 issues to be closed
alone, and I went over things, and checked out some stale issues, to see
if they are dealt with, or pinging authors. I spent like half a day on
this, bring down the issue count by a lot. Tedious work, but must be
done too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also my inbox got a fair amount of cleanup, lots of issues pile up
there, and from time to time, I do this, to get things straight. I
raised issues for 2 things, that I won’t be doing immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But actually as issues go, there really very little problematic stuff
open right now, and nothing important really. I would almost call it
issue clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-5.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very like one you can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goto generator work could be released, but I want to make the
compile all the world test before I do so. It is running right now, but
I will not complete before I leave. Also I do not want to get regression
reports in my holiday, and goto generators along with heap storage, mean
there could be some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to work on C types now. There is a few closing down actions
on what I observed doing goto generators. There are a few easy ways to
get even slightly better performance, definitely smaller code out of
generators. Not sure if I go there first, or for the C types work
directly. I often like to get these kind of observations dealt with more
immediately, but I don’t want to spend too much quality time on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have been asked this, yes, you can donate to Nuitka if you wish to
further its development. Go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-5.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #5</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-08-24T12:55:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-6.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #6</title>
    <updated>2018-09-12T12:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-6"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-6" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#holiday" id="id3"&gt;Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#bool" id="id4"&gt;bool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#void" id="id5"&gt;void&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#module-var" id="id6"&gt;module_var&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id7"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks" id="id8"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id9"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#poll-on-executable-names" id="id10"&gt;Poll on Executable Names&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id11"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id12"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id13"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id14"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="holiday"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my 2 weeks holiday, I indeed focused on a really big thing, and got
more done that I had hoped for. For C types, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka_bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, which is a
tri-state boolean with true, false and unassigned, can be used for some
variables, and executes some operations without going through objects
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="bool"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;bool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Condition codes are no longer special. They all need a boolean value
from the expression used as a condition, and there was a special paths
for some popular expressions for conditions, but of course not all. That
is now a universal thing, conditional statement/expressions will now
simply ask to provide a temp variable of value &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka_bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and then
code generation handles it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For where it is used, code gets a lot lighter, and of course faster,
although I didn’t measure it yet. Going to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Py_True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Py_False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
comparing with it, wasn’t that optimal, and it’s nice this is now so
much cleaner as a side effect of that C bool work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems to be so good, that actually it’s the default for this to be
used in 0.6.0, and that itself is a major break through. Not so much for
actual performance, but for structure. Other C types are going to follow
soon and will give massive performance gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="void"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;void&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what was really good, is that not only did I get &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to work
almost perfectly, I also started work on the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; C target type and
finished that after my return from holiday last weekend, which lead to
new optimization that I am putting in the 0.5.33 release that is coming
soon, even before the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; code generation is out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; C type cannot read values back, and unused values should
not be used, so this gives errors for cases where that becomes obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this expression. The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; expression, that one is going to
producing a value, which is then released, but not used otherwise. New
optimzation creates a conditional statement out of it, which takes &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
as the condition and if not true, then evaluates &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; but ignores it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-python notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; evaluation of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; can then do further optimization for
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Void code generation can therefore highlight missed opportunities for
this kid of optimization, and found a couple of these. That is why I was
going for it, and I feel it pays off. Code generation checking
optimization here, is a really nice synergy between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus I got all the tests to work with it, and solved the missing
optimizations it found very easily. And instead of allocating an object
now, not assigning is often creating more obvious code. And that too
allowed me to find a couple of bugs by C compiler warnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I will want to run a compile all the world test before making
it the default, which is why this will probably become part of 0.6.1 to
be the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="module-var"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;module_var&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously variable codes were making a hard distinction for module
variables and make them use their own helper codes. Now this is
encapsulated in a normal C type class like &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nuitka_bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, or the one
for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; variables, and integrates smoothly, and even got
better. A sign things are going smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still not released. I delayed it after my holiday, and due to the heap
generator change, after stabilizing the C types work, I want to first
finish a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;tests/library/compile_python_module.py&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;resume&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; run, which
will for a Anaconda3 compile all the code found in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now it’s still doing that, and even found a few bugs. The heap
storage can still cause issues, as can changes to cloning nodes, which
happens for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; nodes and their &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;finally&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should finish these days. I looked at performance numbers and found
that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;develop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is indeed only faster, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;factory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; due to even more
optimization will be yet faster, and often noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Speedcenter of Nuitka is what I use right now, but it’s only showing
the state of 3 branches and compared to CPython, not as much historical
information. Also the organization of tests is poor. At least there is
tags for what improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After release of Nuitka 0.6.0 I will show more numbers, and I will start
to focus on making it easier to understand. Therefore no link right now,
google if you are so keen. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the holiday sprint, and even after, I am going to Tweet a lot
about what is going on for Nuitka. So follow me on twitter if you like,
I will post important stuff as it happens there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="poll-on-executable-names"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Poll on Executable Names&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I put e.g. poll up on Twitter, which is now over. But it made me
implement a new scheme, due to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/KayHayen/status/1037591355319640065"&gt;popular consensus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more hotfixes. I even did 2 during my holiday, however packages
built only later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threaded imports on 3.4 or higher of modules were not using the locking
they should use. Multiprocessing on Windows with Python3 had even more
problems, and the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--include-package&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--include-module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; were
present, but not working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one was actually very strange. I had added a new option group
for them, but not added it to the parser. Result: Option works. Just
does not show up in help output. Really?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-6.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very like one you can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working down the release backlog. Things should be out. I am already
working on what should become 0.6.1, but it’s not yet 0.5.33 released.
Not a big deal, but 0.6.0 has 2 really important fixes for performance
regressions that have happened in the past. One is for loops, making
that faster is probably like the most important one. The other for
constant indexing, probably also very important. Very much measurable in
pystone at least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I am preparing to get &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; working as a target C
type, so e.g. comparisons of such values could be done in pure C, or
relatively pure C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I noticed that e.g. in-place operations can be way more optimized
and did stuff for 0.6.1 already in this domain. That is unrelated to C
type work, but kind of follows a similar route maybe. How to compare
mixed types we know of, or one type only. That kind of things needs
ideas and experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; supported should help getting some functions to C speeds,
or at least much closer to it. That will make noticeable effects in many
of the benchmarks. More C types will then follow one by one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-6.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #6</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-09-12T12:05:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-7.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #7</title>
    <updated>2018-09-22T11:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-7"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-7" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-design-philosophy" id="id3"&gt;Nuitka Design Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#ui-rework" id="id4"&gt;UI rework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#goto-generators" id="id5"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks" id="id6"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id7"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id8"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#egg-files-in-pythonpath" id="id9"&gt;Egg files in PYTHONPATH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#certifi" id="id10"&gt;Certifi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#compatibility-with-pkg-resources" id="id11"&gt;Compatibility with pkg_resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id12"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="nuitka-design-philosophy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Nuitka Design Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this as part of a discussion recently, and I think it makes
sense to share my take on Nuitka and design. This is a lot text
though, feel free to skip forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with Nuitka and design mainly for me is that the requirements
for many parts were and are largely unknown to me, until I actually
start to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goto generators approach worked out as originally designed, and that
felt really cool for once, but the whole “C type” thing was a total
unknown to me, until it all magically took form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But rather I know it will evolve further if I go from “bool” (complete
and coming for 0.6.0) via “void” (should be complete already, but
enabling will happen only for 0.6.1 likely) to “int”, not sure how long
that will take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think Nuitka, unlike other software that I have designed, is
more of a prototype project that gradually turns more and more into the
real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have literally spent &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; to inject proper design in steps into the
optimization phase, what I call SSA, value tracing, and it is very much
there now. I am probably going to spend similar amounts of time, to
execute on applying type inference results to the code generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I turned that into something working with code strings to something
working with variable declaration objects knowing their type for the
goto generators, aiming at C types generally. All the while carrying the
full weight of passing every compatibility test there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then e.g. suddenly cleaning up module variables to no longer have their
special branch, but a pseudo C type, that makes them like everything
else. Great. But when I first introduced the new thing, I postponed
that, because I could sooner apply its benefits to some things and get
experience from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While doing partial solutions, the design sometimes horribly degrades,
but only until some features can carry the full weight, and/or have been
explored to have their final form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a whole Nuitka design upfront and then executing it, would
instead give a very high probability of failing in the real world. I am
therefore applying the more agile approach, where I make things work
first. And then continue to work while I clean it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every feature I added, I actively go out, and change the thing, that
made it hard or even fail. Always. I think Nuitka is largely developed
by cleanups and refactoring. Goto generators were a fine example of
that, solving many of the issues by injecting variable declarations
objects into code generation, made it easy to indicate storage (heap or
object or stack) right there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that Nuitka didn’t have the typical compiler design.
Like parsing inputs, optimizing a tree internally, producing outputs.
But that grand top level design only tells you the obvious things really
and is stolen anyway from knowing similar projects like gcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There always were of course obvious designs for Nuitka, but that really
never was what anybody would consider to make a Python compiler hard.
But for actual compatibility of CPython, so many details were going to
require examination with no solutions known ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess, I am an extreme programmer, or agile, or however they call it
these days. At least for Nuitka. In my professional life, I have
designed software for ATC on the drawing board, then in paper, and then
in code, the design just worked, and got operational right after
completion, which is rare I can tell you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe that is what keeps me exciting about Nuitka. How I need to go
beyond my abilities and stable ground to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the complexity of Nuitka is so dramatically higher than anything I
ever did. It is doing a complicated, i.e. detail rich work, and then it
also is doing hard jobs where many things have to play together. And the
wish to have something working before it is completed, if it ever is,
makes things very different from projects I typically did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the first version of Nuitka already had a use, and when I publicly
showed it first, was capable of handling most complex programs, and the
desire was to evolve gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I have described this elsewhere, but for large parts of the well
or bad designed solutions of Nuitka, there is reliable ways of
demonstrating it works correctly. Far better than I have ever
encountered. i believe it’s the main reason I managed to get this off
the ground is that. Having a test “oracle” is what makes Nuitka special,
i.e. comparing to existing implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a calculator can be tested comparing it to one of the many already
perfect ones out there. That again makes Nuitka relatively easy despite
the many details to get right, there is often an easy way to tell
correct from wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for me, Nuitka is on the design level, something that goes through
many iterations, discovery, prototyping, and is actually really exciting
in that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compilers typically are boring. But for Nuitka that is totally not the
case, because Python is not made for it. Well, that*s technically
untrue, lets say not for optimizing compilers, not for type inference,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ui-rework"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;UI rework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following up on discussion on the mailing list, the user interface of
Nuitka will become more clear with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--include-*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; options and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--[no]follow-import*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; options that better express what is going to
happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the default for following with extension modules is now precisely
what you say, as going beyond what you intend to deliver makes no sense
in the normal case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goto-generators"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Goto Generators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now release as 0.5.33 and there has been little regressions so far, but
the one found is only in the pre-release of 0.6.0 so use that instead if
you encounter a C compilation error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance regressions fixed for 0.6.0 impact &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pystone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; by a lot,
loops were slower, so were subscripts with constant integer indexes. It
is a pity these were introduced in previous releases during refactorings
without noticing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should strive to have benchmarks with trends. Right now Nuitka
speedcenter cannot do it. Focus should definitely go to this. Like I
said, after 0.6.0 release, this will be a priority, to make them more
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be active there. I just put out a poll about the comment
system, and disabling Disqus comments I will focus on Twitter for web
site comments too now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-7.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="egg-files-in-pythonpath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Egg files in PYTHONPATH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a relatively old issue that now got addressed. Basically these
should be loaded from for compilation. Nuitka now unpacks them to a
cache folder so it can read source code from them, so this apparently
rare use case works now, yet again improving compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will be there for 0.6.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="certifi"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Certifi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems request module sometimes uses that. Nuitka now includes that data
file starting with 0.6.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="compatibility-with-pkg-resources"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Compatibility with pkg_resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that getting “distributions” and taking versions from there, is
really a thing, and Nuitka fails pkg_resources requirement checks in
standalone mode at least, and that is of course sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently researching how to fix that, not sure yet how to do it.
But some forms of Python installs are apparently very affected by it. I
try looking into its data gathering, maybe compiled modules can be
registered there too. It seems to be based on file system scans of its
own makings, but there is always a monkey patch possible to make it
better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still working on the 0.6.0 release, cleaning up open ends only. Release
tests seem to be pretty good looking. The UI changes and stuff are a
good time to be done now, but delay things, and there is a bunch of
small things that are low hanging fruits while I wait for test results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since it fixes so many performance things, it really ought to be out
any day now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the in-place operations stuff, I added it to 0.6.0 too, just
because it feels very nice, and improves some operations by a lot too.
Initially I had made a cut for 0.6.1 already, but that is no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-7.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #7</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-09-22T11:05:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-8.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #8</title>
    <updated>2018-10-02T06:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-8"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-8" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#public-private-ci-workflow" id="id3"&gt;Public / Private CI / Workflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#workflow" id="id4"&gt;Workflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hunting-bugs-with-bisect" id="id5"&gt;Hunting bugs with bisect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#experimental-changes" id="id6"&gt;Experimental Changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hardware" id="id7"&gt;Hardware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#milestone-release" id="id8"&gt;Milestone Release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#ui-rework" id="id9"&gt;UI rework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks" id="id10"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#inplace-operations" id="id11"&gt;Inplace Operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#new-use-cases" id="id12"&gt;New use cases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#tcl-tk-standalone" id="id13"&gt;Tcl/Tk Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#caching-examined" id="id14"&gt;Caching Examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id15"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id16"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plans" id="id17"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id18"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="public-private-ci-workflow"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Public / Private CI / Workflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this as part of a discussion recently, and I think it makes
sense to share it here. This is a lot text though, feel free to skip
forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed I have a private repo, where I push and only private CI picks up.
Based on Buildbot, I run many more compilations, basically around the
clock on all of my computers, to find regressions from new optimization
or codegen changes, and well UI changes too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public CI offerings like Travis are not aimed at allowing this many
compilations. It will be a while before public cloud infrastructure will
be donated to Nuitka, although I see it happening some time in the
future. This leaves developers with the burden to run tests on their own
hardware, and never enough. Casual contributors will never be able to do
it themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My scope is running the CPython test suites on Windows and Linux. These
are the adapted 26, 27, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37 suites, and also to get
even more errors covered, they are ran with mismatching Python versions,
so a lot of exceptions are raised. Often running the 36 tests with 37
and vice versa will extend the coverage, because of the exceptions being
raise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows I compile with and without debug mode, x86 and x64, and it’s
kind of getting too much. For Linux I have 2 laptops in use, and an ARM
CuBox bought from your donations, there it’s working better, esp. due to
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; being used everywhere, although recent investigations show
room for improvement there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For memory usage I still compile mercurial and observe the memory it
used in addition to comparing the mercurial tests to expected outputs
its test suite gives. It’s a sad day when Mercurial tests find changes
in behavior, and luckily that has been rare. Running the Mercurial test
suite gives some confidence in the thing not corrupting data it works
with without knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caching the CPython outputs of tests to compare against is something I
am going to make operational these days, trying to make things ever
faster. There is no point to re-run tests with Python, just to get at
its output, which will typically not change at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the time being, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache.exe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;clcache.exe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; seem to have
done wonders for Windows too, but I will want to investigate some more
to avoid unnecessary cache misses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="workflow"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Workflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my workflow with Nuitka, I often tend to let some commits settle
in my private repo only until they become trusted. Other times I will
make bigger changes and put them out to factory immediately, because it
will be hard to split up the changes later, so putting them out makes it
easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am more conservative with factory right after telling people to try
something there. But also I break it on purpose, just trying out
something. I really consider it a private branch for interacting with me
or public CI. I do not recommend to use it, and it’s like a permanent
pull request of mine that is not ever going to be finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on occasions I am making a sorting of all commits on factory and
split it into some things that become hotfixes, some things that become
current pre-release, and other things that will remain in that proving
ground. That is why I typically make hotfix and pre-release at the same
times. The git flow suggests doing that and it’s easy, so why not. As a
bonus, develop is then practically stable at nearly all times too, with
hardly any regressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do however normally not take things as hotfixes that are on develop
already, I hate the duplication of commits. Hotfixes must be small and
risk free, and easy to put out, when there is any risk, it definitely
will be on develop. Nuitka stable typically covers nearly all grounds
already. No panic needed to add missing stuff and break others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hunting-bugs-with-bisect"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Hunting bugs with bisect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the git bisect is very important. My private commit history is
basically a total mess and worthless, but on factory I am making very
nice organized commits that I will frequently amend, even for the random
PyLint cleanup. This allows me when e.g. one test suddenly says
“segfault” on Windows to easily find the change that triggers it, look
at C code difference, and spot the bug introduced, then amend the commit
and be done with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how much time this can save. My goal is to always have a
workable state which is supposed to pass all tests. Obviously I cannot
prove it for every commit, but when I know it to not be the case, I tend
to make rebases. At times I have been tempted and followed up on
backward amending develop and even stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am doing that to be sure to have that bisect ability, but fortunately
it’s rare that kind of bug occurs, and I try not to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="experimental-changes"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Experimental Changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with recent changes, I sometimes make changes with the
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;isExperimental()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; marker, activating breaking changes only gradually.
The C &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; type code generation has been there for months in a
barely useful form, until it became more polished, and always guarded
with a switch, until one day for 0.6 finally I changed it, and made the
necessary fixes retroactively before that switch, to make it work while
that was still in factory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I will remove the experimental code. I feel it’s very important and
even ideal to be able to always compare outputs to a fully working
solution. I am willing to postpone some cleanups until later date as a
price, but when then something in my mind tells me again “This cannot
possibly have ever worked”… a command line flag away, I have the
answer to compare, plus, that includes extra changes happened in the
meantime, they don’t add noise to diff outputs of generated C code for
example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then looking at that diff, I can tell where the unwanted effect is, and
fix all the things, and that way find bugs much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, if I decide to make a cleanup action as part of making a
change more viable to execute, then I get to execute it on stable
grounds, covered by the full test suite. I can complete that cleanup,
e.g. using variable identifier objects instead of mere strings was
needed to make “heap generators” more workable. But I was able to put
that one to active before “heap generators” was ever fully workable, and
complete it, and actually reap some of its benefits already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hardware"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Hardware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this takes a lot of hardware and CPU to be able to compile
this much Python code on a regular basis. And I really wish I could add
one of the new AMD Threadripper 2 to the mix. Anybody donating one to
me? Yes I know, I am only dreaming. But it would really help the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="milestone-release"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Milestone Release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the 0.6 is out, and already a hotfix that addresses mostly use cases
of people that didn’t work. More people seemed to have tried out 0.6.0
and as a result 0.6.0.1 is going to cover a few corner cases. So far I
have not encountered a single regression of 0.6.0, but instead it
contained ones for 0.5.33 which did have one that was not easy to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that went really smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ui-rework"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;UI rework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UI needs more work still. Specifically that packages do not
automatically include all stuff below them and have to be specified by
file path instead of by name, is really annoying to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I had delayed 0.6 for some UI work, and the quirks are to remain
some. I will work on these things eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I updated the website to state that PyStone is now 312% faster, from
a number that was very old. I since then ran it with an updated version
for Python3, and it’s much less there. That is pretty sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be looking into that for 0.6.1 release, or I will have to update
the wording to provide 2 numbers there, because it seems for Python3
performance with Nuitka it might be misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something with unicode strings and in-place operations is driving me
crazy. Nuitka is apparently slower for that, and I can’t point where
that is happening exactly. It seems internally unicode objects are maybe
put into a different state from some operations, which then making
in-place extending in realloc fail more often, but I cannot know yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="inplace-operations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Inplace Operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So more work has been put into those, adding more specialization, and
esp. also applying them for module variables as well. CPython can do
that, and actually is giving itself a hard time about it, and Nuitka
should be doing this much clever with its more static knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I cannot tell you how much scratching my head was wasted debugging
that. I was totally stupid about how I approached that, looking from the
final solution, it was always easy. Just not for me apparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="new-use-cases"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;New use cases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talked about those above. So the top level &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;logging&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module of your
own was working fine in accelerated mode, but for standalone it failed
and used the one from standard library instead. That kind of shadowing
happened because Nuitka was going from module objects to their names and
back to objects, which are bad in case of duplicates. That is fixed for
develop, and one of those risk cases, where it cannot be a hotfix
because it touched too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then pure Python3 packages need not have &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__init__.py&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and so far that
was best working for sub-packages, but after 0.6.0.1 hotfix, now it will
also work for the main module you compile to be that empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="tcl-tk-standalone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Tcl/Tk Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instructions have been provided how to properly make that work for
Python standalone on Windows. I have yet to live up to my promise and
make Nuitka automatically include the necessary files. I hope to do it
for 0.6.1 though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="caching-examined"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Caching Examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am looking at ccache on Linux right now, and found e.g. that it was
reporting that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;gcc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;--version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; was called a lot at startup of Scons
and then &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;g++&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;--version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; once. The later is particularly stupid,
because we are not going to use g++ normally, except if gcc is really
old and does not support C11. So in case a good one was found, lets
disable that version query and not do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the gcc version output, monkey patching scons to a version of
getting that output that caches the result, removes those unnecessary
forks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is being called less frequently, and actually these
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; outputs appears to actually take measurable time. It’s not
dramatic, but &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; was apparently getting locks, and that’s worth
avoiding by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, the goal is for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;clcache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to make them both
report their effectiveness of cache usage after the end of a test suite
run. That way I am hoping to notice and be able to know, if caching is
used to its full effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be very active there. I put out a poll about the comment
system, and disabling Disqus comments as a result, I will focus on
Twitter for web site comments too now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-8.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on the 0.6.1 release, attacking more in-place add operations as
a first goal, and now turning to binary operations, I am trying to shape
how using different helper functions to different object types looks
like. And to gain performance without C types. But ultimately the same
issue will arise there, what to do with mixed input types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My desire is for in-place operations to fully catch up with CPython, as
these can easily loose a lot of performance. Closure variables and their
cells are another target to pick on, and I feel they ought to be next
after module ones are now working, because also their solution ought to
be very similar. Then showing that depending on target storage, local,
closure, or module, is then faster in all cases would be a goal for the
0.6.1 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels not too far away, but we will see. I am considering next
weekend for release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-8.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #8</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-10-02T06:05:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-9.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #9</title>
    <updated>2018-10-20T06:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-9"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-9" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#communication-vs-coding" id="id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id4"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka" id="id5"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#website-overhaul" id="id6"&gt;Website Overhaul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance-work" id="id7"&gt;Performance Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#adding-specialized-object-operations" id="id8"&gt;Adding specialized object operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#finding-missing-specialized-object-code-generation" id="id9"&gt;Finding missing specialized object code generation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimizing-plain-object-operations-too" id="id10"&gt;Optimizing plain object operations too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#lack-of-type-knowledge" id="id11"&gt;Lack of type knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance-regressions-vs-cpython" id="id12"&gt;Performance regressions vs. CPython&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#in-place-unicode-still-being-bad" id="id13"&gt;In-place unicode still being bad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks-missing" id="id14"&gt;Benchmarks Missing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#type-shapes-in-optimization" id="id15"&gt;Type shapes in optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#control-flow-escape" id="id16"&gt;Control flow escape&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#overall" id="id17"&gt;Overall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#improved-annotations" id="id18"&gt;Improved Annotations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#release-or-not" id="id19"&gt;Release or not&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#standalone-improvements" id="id20"&gt;Standalone Improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#caching-examined" id="id21"&gt;Caching Examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#python3-deprecation-warnings" id="id22"&gt;Python3 deprecation warnings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id23"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id24"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id25"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-vs-coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new communication strategy is a full success, engagement with Nuitka
is on an all time high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the recent weeks more than ever highlighted why I have to force
myself to do it. I do not like to talk about unfinished stuff. And right
now, there is really a lot of it, almost only it. Also I was ill, and
otherwise busy, so this is now late by a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am keeping it up, and will give an update, despite the feeling
that it would be better to just finish a few of those things and then
talk about it, but then it will take forever and leave you in the dark.
And that is not what is supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, that this is supposed to be a quick, not too polished, and
straight from top of my head, even if really a lot of content. But I
feel that esp. the optimization parts are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the 0.6.0 release was a huge success, but it definitely wasn’t
perfect, and hotfixes were necessary. The latest one 0.6.0.5 was done
just yesterday and actually contains one for an important
mis-optimization being done, and you ought to update to it from any
prior 0.6.0 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a few remaining compatibility issues fixed for 3.7 and
generally using the latest hotfix is always a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kind of what one has to expect from a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; release, this one also had
more expose than usual is seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need more people to work on Nuitka. One way of doing this could be to
participate in Google Summer of Code under the Python umbrella. To make
that possible, I need you to volunteer as a mentor. So please, please,
do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know you will feel not qualified. But I just need a backup that will
help a student around obstacles in case I go missing. Contact me and I
will be very happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="website-overhaul"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Website Overhaul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I updated the website to recent Nikola and dropped the tag cloud that I
was using. Should have cleaner and better looks. Also integrated privacy
aware sharing links, where two clicks are necessary to share a page or
article like this one on Twitter, Facebook, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the download page saw some structural updates and polishing. It
should easier to overview now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Performance Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="adding-specialized-object-operations"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Adding specialized object operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback for performance and the work on 0.6.1 are fully ongoing,
and there are many major points that are ongoing. I want to briefly
cover each one of them now, but many of them will only have full effect,
once everything is in place, which each one is very critical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with the type tracing, objects have known types, and short of using
a C type, knowing e.g. that an object is an &lt;cite&gt;int&lt;/cite&gt;, and the other one
too, doing &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; for them can take a lot of advantage avoiding unrelated
checks and code paths, even if still using &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; at the end of
the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even we are only knowing it’s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, but say one value is
a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;tuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and the other an unknown, that allows to remove checks for
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; shortcuts as they can no longer apply. These are tiny
optimizations then, but still worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further this, first the inplace operations for a couple of more or
less randomly selected types, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;tuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;bytes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, have been looked at and
have gotten their own special object based helpers if one or both types
are known to be of that kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="finding-missing-specialized-object-code-generation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Finding missing specialized object code generation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A report has been added, that will tell when such an operation could
have been used, but was not available. This uncovered where typical
stuff goes non optimized, a nice principle to see what is actually
happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So adding &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; would now give a warning, although of
course, the optimization phase ought to catch the static raise that is
and never let it get there, so this report also addresses missing
optimization in an earlier phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimizing-plain-object-operations-too"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Optimizing plain object operations too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the in-place operations were then covered, so this was extended to
mere &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; operations too, the ones that are not in-place. Sometimes,
esp. for immutable types, there was already code for that, e.g. &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
doesn’t really do it, in other cases, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; code for a
quicker concat was added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again a report for where it’s missing was added and basic coverage
for most of the types. However, in some instances, the optimization
doesn’t use the full knowledge yet. But where it does, it will shove off
quite a few cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="lack-of-type-knowledge"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Lack of type knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply these things effectively, optimization and value tracing need
to know types in the first place. I have found two obstacles for that.
One are branch merges. If a branch or both assign to the same type or
original type, well the type is changed. Previously it became “unknown”
which is treated as &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for code generation, and allows nothing
really. But now that is better on develop now, and was actually a
trivial missing thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other area is loops. Loops put values to unknown when entering loop
body, and again when leaving. Essentially making type tracing not
effective where it is needed the most to achieve actual performance.
Also this was limiting the knowledge for all function to one type to not
happening for these kinds of variables that were assigned inside a loop
at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Took me a while, but I figured out how to build type tracing for loops
that works. It currently is still unfinished in my private repo, but
passes all tests, I would just like to make it use dedicated interfaces,
and clean it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will most likely have that for 0.6.1 too and that should expand the
cases where types are known in code generation by a fair amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of that will be that more often C code generation will
actually see types. Currently e.g. a boolean variable that is assigned
in a loop, cannot use the C target type in code generation. Once loop
code is merged, it will however take advantage there too. And only then
I think adding “C int” as a C type makes sense at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance-regressions-vs-cpython"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Performance regressions vs. CPython&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then another area is performance regressions. So one thing I did early
on in the 0.6.1 cycle was using the “module var C target type” to get
in-place working for those too. Doing string concatenations on module
variables could be slower by an order of magnitude, as could be other
operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still need to do it for closure variables too. Then Nuitka will do at
least as many of them perfectly as CPython does. It also will be better
at it them, because e.g. it doesn’t have to delete from the module
dictionary first, due to it never taking a reference, and same applies
to the cell. Should be faster for that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But strings in-place on these if not optimized, it will look very ugly
in terms of worse performance, so 0.6.0 was still pretty bad for some
users. This will however hopefully be addressed in 0.6.1 then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-place-unicode-still-being-bad"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;In-place unicode still being bad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another field was in-place string add for the already optimized case, it
was still slower than CPython, and I finally found out what causes this.
And that is the using of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libpython&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PyUnicode_Append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is far
worse than in the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;python&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; binary that you normally use, I have see
that at least for 3.5 and higher CPython. Analysis showed that e.g.
MiniConda had the issue to a much smaller extent, and was being much
faster anyway, but probably just has better &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libpython&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; compilation
flags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what to do. Ultimately that was to be solved by including a clone of
that function, dubbed &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;UNICODE_APPEND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; that behaves the same, and can
even shove off a couple of cycles, by indicating the Python error status
without extra checks, and specializing it for the pure &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; case that we see most often, same for &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;UNICODE_CONCAT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for
mere &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now the benchmarks to show it do not exist yet. Again something
that typically wants me to delay stuff. But as you can imagine, tracking
down these hard issues, writing that much code to replace the unicode
resizing, is hard enough by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I hope to convince myself that this will allow to show that for
compiled code, things are going to be faster only now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks-missing"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Benchmarks Missing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, speedcenter as a whole is currently broken, mostly due to
Nikola changes that I am trying to work around, but it will take more
time apparently and isn’t finished as I write this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="type-shapes-in-optimization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Type shapes in optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another optimization end, is the type shapes of the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; operation
itself. Right now what is being done is that the shape is derived from
the shape of the left argument with the right shape to be considered by
it. These also have reports now, for cases where they are missing. So
saying e.g. that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; results in &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and these
kinds of things, are stuff being encoded there right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is necessary step to e.g. know that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt;
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int_or_long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, to make effective loop variable optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without these, and again, that is a lot of code to write, there is no
way to hope for wide spread type knowledge in code generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="control-flow-escape"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Control flow escape&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something missing there, is to also make it known that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; unlike it
currently is now, should not in all cases lead to “control flow escape”
with the consequence of removing all stuff, and expecting an exception
possible, but instead to let the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; type also make known that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; ont it not only gives an &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int_or_long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; result shape, but also
while doing so, that it will never raise an exception (bare
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;MemoryError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;), and therefore allow more optimization to happen and
less and therefore faster code generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until this is done, what is actually going to happen is that while the
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; result is known, Nuitka will assume control flow escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of that, I think this puts too many variables to a too
unknown state. You can to distrust all values, but not the types in this
case, so that could be better, but right now it is not. Something else
to look into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="overall"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;Overall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 0.6.1 is in full swing in terms of optimization. All these ends need
a completion, and then I can expect to use advantage of things in a
loop, and ultimately to generate C performance code for one example of
loop. esp. if we add a C &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; target type, which currently isn’t yet
started, because I think it would barely be used yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we are getting there and I wouldn’t even say we are making small
steps, this is all just work to be completed, nothing fundamental about
it. But it may take more than one release for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind you, there is not only &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, there is also &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;,
and many more operators, all of them will require work. Granted, loop
variables tend to use &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; more often, but any un-optimized operation
will immediately loose a lot of type knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="improved-annotations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Improved Annotations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of annotations, ones for classes and modules, which
actually are stored in a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__annotations__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; variable, and everything
else is mostly just ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Nuitka got the criterion wrong, and did one thing for functions, and
the other for everything else. So that annotations in generators,
coroutines and asyncgen ended up with wrong, crashing, and slower code,
due to it updating the module &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__annotations__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, so that one is
important too if you have to do those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="release-or-not"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id19"&gt;Release or not&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To release or not. There is at least one bug about star imports that
affects numpy that is solved in develop, and wasn’t back ported, and I
was thinking it only applies to develop, but in fact does to stable. It
makes me want to release even before all these optimization things
happen and are polished, and I might well decide to go with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I only add the closure in-place stuff and the polish the loop SSA
stuff, and then call it a release. It already will solve a lot of
performance issues that exist right now, while staging the ground for
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="standalone-improvements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id20"&gt;Standalone Improvements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standalone work is also improving. Using pyi files got more apt, and a
few things were added, all of which make sense to be used by people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also have a backlog of issues there however. I will schedule one
sprint for those I guess, where I focus on these. I am neglecting those
somewhat recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="caching-examined"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id21"&gt;Caching Examined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the static code, I now noticed that it’s compiled for each target
name, due to the build directory being part of the object file for
debug. For gcc 8 there is an option to allow pointing at the original
static C file location, and then &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ccache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is more effective, because
object files will be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s actually pretty bad, as most of my machines are on &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;gcc-6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
makes me think that &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libnuitka.a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is really more of an requirement
than ever. I might take some time to get this sorted out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python3-deprecation-warnings"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id22"&gt;Python3 deprecation warnings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Nuitka supports the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;no_warnings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; Python flag, and for a long time
I have been annoyed at how it was not working for Python3 in some cases.
The code was manually settign filters, but these would get overridden by
CPython test suites testing warnings. And the code said that there is no
CPython C-API to control it, which is just plain wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I changed that and it became possible to remove lots of
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;ignore_stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; annotations in CPython test suites, and more
importantly, I can stop adding them for when running older/newer CPython
version with a suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id23"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be very active there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id24"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-9.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id25"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-9.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #9</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-10-20T06:17:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-10.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #10</title>
    <updated>2018-11-21T06:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-10"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-10" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#communication-vs-coding" id="id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#hotfixes" id="id4"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka" id="id5"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#pythran-and-nuitka" id="id6"&gt;Pythran and Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance-work" id="id7"&gt;Performance Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#adding-specialized-object-operations" id="id8"&gt;Adding specialized object operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#controlflow-descriptions" id="id9"&gt;Controlflow Descriptions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#preparations-for-comparison-operations" id="id10"&gt;Preparations for comparison operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#comparison-conditions" id="id11"&gt;Comparison Conditions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#local-variable-escaping" id="id12"&gt;Local variable escaping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#benchmarks-missing" id="id13"&gt;Benchmarks Missing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#static-linking" id="id14"&gt;Static Linking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#conda-cc" id="id15"&gt;Conda CC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#annotations-future-feature" id="id16"&gt;Annotations Future Feature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#msi-files" id="id17"&gt;MSI files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#overall" id="id18"&gt;Overall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id19"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id20"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id21"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-vs-coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently it was a bit more tough to make that decision. First, there was
much going privately, with me ill, then child ill, and ill again, and
myself, and that made me have a much harder time to communicate about
incomplete things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even now, I am torn between fixing issues for 0.6.1 and doing this, but
I know that it will take at least one week, so I am missing the point,
if I wait for it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, that this is supposed to be a quick, not too polished, and
straight from top of my head, even if really a lot of content. But I
feel that esp. the optimization parts are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="hotfixes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Hotfixes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been another hotfix, 0.6.0.6 and there ought to be one
0.6.0.7, at least on factory there is a bunch of stuff for it, but I
didn’t actually do it yet. I was wandering between there will be a
release anyway, and the feeling that some of the material may cause
regressions, so I might skip on that really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for the most fixes, I suspect, develop is going to be the way until
next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody has stepped up, which means it will not happen unfortunately.
This would be your last chance to step up. I know you will feel not
qualified. But I just need a backup that will help a student around
obstacles in case I go missing. Contact me and I will be very happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pythran-and-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Pythran and Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As suggested by &amp;#64;wuoulf (Wolf Vollprecht) we had a meeting at the side
of the PyCon DE 2018 conference in Karlsruhe, abusing the C++ regular
table as a forum for that, which was a very nice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, Wolf is so much more knowledgeable about AnaConda and
could point out to me, very important stuff, not the least, that
AnaConda contains its own compiler, which I have successfully used
since, to first add easier installation instructions for Windows, and
second, to successfully statically link with LTO on Linux amd64. Both of
which are important for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for Pythran which is limited Python, specialized to translate Numpy
API to C++, we showed each other, Nuitka and Pythran details, and
somehow in my mind a plan formed how Nuitka could use the Pythran tricks
long term, and mid term, how it could include a plugin that will allow
to integrate with Pythran compilation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a huge success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Performance Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="adding-specialized-object-operations"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Adding specialized object operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See last week, this has seen more completion. Both &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;+=&lt;/cite&gt; are more
or less covered for the selected subset. The CPython test suites were
initially not finding uses, but with more and more optimization phase
improvements, it challenges code generation with missing ones, and then
I added them more and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="controlflow-descriptions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Controlflow Descriptions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shapes were added for the &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/cite&gt; operation so far, but didn’t
influence anything else really but code generation, but of course they
should also impact optimization phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the query for type shape has been enhanced to return not only a type
shape saying that &lt;cite&gt;int+float -&amp;gt; float&lt;/cite&gt;, but also now an object that
describes impact on control flow of the program. This can then say e.g.
that this doesn’t execute arbitrary code, and that it does not modify
input values, things used in the code generation to avoid error checks,
and in the optimization to not have to mark things as unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="preparations-for-comparison-operations"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Preparations for comparison operations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So optimization now also has proper type shape functions for the &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/cite&gt; and
the warnings when they fail to know what to do for concrete types. This
allows to actually remove checks, but so far this wasn’t exposed for
neither &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; or for &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/cite&gt;. Doing this eliminates the exception check for
the operation part, where previously it was done if anything in the
expression could raise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specializing the rich comparisons helper codes is the next step, but so
far I didn’t quite get to it yet, but it has been started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="comparison-conditions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Comparison Conditions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparing &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/cite&gt; optimization for the loop, I noticed that &lt;cite&gt;not&lt;/cite&gt; was
optimized for &lt;cite&gt;in&lt;/cite&gt; to become &lt;cite&gt;not in&lt;/cite&gt;, and also &lt;cite&gt;is&lt;/cite&gt; to become &lt;cite&gt;is not&lt;/cite&gt;,
etc. but for comparisons, where we can not the result is of bool shape,
we can now also switch &lt;cite&gt;not &amp;lt;&lt;/cite&gt; to &lt;cite&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;not =&lt;/cite&gt; to &lt;cite&gt;!=&lt;/cite&gt; of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since our reformulation of &lt;cite&gt;while a &amp;lt; b&lt;/cite&gt; ends up having a statement
like &lt;cite&gt;if not a &amp;lt; b: break&lt;/cite&gt; as part of its re-formulation, that is again
one step closer to optimizing my example loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="local-variable-escaping"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Local variable escaping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much to my shock, I noticed that the code which is responsible to handle
escaping control flow (i.e. unknown code is executed), was not only
doing what it was supposed to do, i.e. mark closure variables as
unknown, but more or less did it for all local variables with Python3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixing that allows for a lot more optimization obviously, and makes my
test find missing ones, and even bugs in existing ones, that were
previously hidden. A good thing to notice this regression (was better
once), now that I am looking at concrete examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One noticeable sign was that more of my tests failed with warnings about
missing code helpers. And another that in my while loop with &lt;cite&gt;int&lt;/cite&gt;
increase, it now seems as if Python3 is good. For Python2, the “int or
long” shape will need dedicated helpers. That is because &lt;cite&gt;ìnt + int&lt;/cite&gt;
becomes either &lt;cite&gt;int&lt;/cite&gt; or &lt;cite&gt;long&lt;/cite&gt; there, where Python3 only has &lt;cite&gt;long&lt;/cite&gt; but
renamed it &lt;cite&gt;int&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="benchmarks-missing"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Benchmarks Missing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speedcenter got repaired, but I need to add the loop examples I am using
as test cases before next release, so I can show what Nuitka 0.6.1 will
have achieved or at least have improved somewhat already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But currently these examples only serve as input for general
improvements that then take a lot of time, and don’t have immediate
impact on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still would be good to see where Nuitka is standing after each one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="static-linking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Static Linking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So static linking works now, provided it’s not a &lt;cite&gt;pyenv&lt;/cite&gt; crappy
&lt;cite&gt;libpython.a&lt;/cite&gt; but one that can actually work. I got this to work on
Linux and using the Conda CC, even LTO will work with it. Interestingly
then linking is noticely slow, and I bet &lt;cite&gt;ccache&lt;/cite&gt; and the likes won’t
help with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am interested to see what this means for performance impact. But it
will allow to address issues, where embedded CPython run time is plain
slower than the one that lives in the python binary. For acceleration
this is great news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conda-cc"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Conda CC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Conda CC by default as a fallback in &lt;cite&gt;–mingw&lt;/cite&gt; mode on Windows is
something that was easy to add. So when no other &lt;cite&gt;gcc&lt;/cite&gt; is found, and
MSVC is not tried in this mode, and the right directory is added to
&lt;cite&gt;PATH&lt;/cite&gt; automatically, with Anaconda, things should now be smoother. It
has also its own &lt;cite&gt;libpython.a&lt;/cite&gt;, not sure yet if it’s a static link
library, that would be fantastic, but unlike standard MinGW64 we do not
have to roll our own at least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try with &lt;cite&gt;–lto&lt;/cite&gt; eventually though and see what it does. But I
think static linking on Windows is not supported by CPython, but I am
not entirely sure of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="annotations-future-feature"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Annotations Future Feature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Found a 3.7 feature that is not covered by the test suite, the
&lt;cite&gt;__future__&lt;/cite&gt; flag &lt;cite&gt;annotations&lt;/cite&gt; wasn’t working as expected. In this,
strings are to be used for &lt;cite&gt;__annotations__&lt;/cite&gt; where they show up (many
are ignored simply) and that requires an &lt;cite&gt;unparse&lt;/cite&gt; function, going from
parsed ast (presumably it’s still syntax checked) back to the string,
but that was only very hard to get at, and with evil hackery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 3.8 a bug fix is promised that will give us the string immediately,
but for now my hack must suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="msi-files"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;MSI files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the 3.7.1 release, there are MSI files again, as the
regression of 3.7.0 to build them has been fixed in that release. The
MSI files will work with 3.7.0 also, just the building was broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="overall"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Overall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 0.6.1 is in still in full swing in terms of optimization. I think I
need to make a release soon, simply because there is too much
unreleased, but useful stuff already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might have to postpone my goal of C int performance for one example
loop until next release. No harm in that. There already are plenty of
performance improvements across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id19"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be very active there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id20"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-10.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id21"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-10.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #10</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-11-21T06:06:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-11.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #11</title>
    <updated>2018-12-10T07:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-11"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-11" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#communication-vs-coding" id="id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimization-work" id="id4"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#levels-of-optimization" id="id5"&gt;Levels of Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#week-of-bugfixing" id="id6"&gt;Week of Bugfixing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#exec-on-filehandles" id="id7"&gt;Exec on Filehandles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#pkgutil-iter-modules" id="id8"&gt;pkgutil.iter_modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#when-to-release" id="id9"&gt;When to release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka" id="id10"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id11"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id12"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-vs-coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to force myself to report more publicly, and it feels good.
This time things are in a stablizing period, and I feel I have a
consistent message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, that this is supposed to be a quick, not too polished, and
straight from top of my head, even if really a lot of content. But I
feel that esp. the optimization parts are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the 0.6.1 optimization work has been a lot. And it’s containing
improvements on every level. I think I will detail the levels in another
section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="levels-of-optimization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Levels of Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First level is of course node level optimization. Here 0.6.1 adds many
things, from better handling of closure variables not all as unknown
every time control flow escapes, to some operations &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
comparisons on known built-in type shapes to now be able to statically
tell that they do not raise. The opposite (does definitely raise) is
prepared, but not yet used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows for type shapes to be longer known. Now &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;a+b+c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; can be
known, but previously only &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;a+b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; was sort of known, and little used
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next level is picking the C target type. Here seeing more operations
and understanding more variables allows to more often pick the &lt;cite&gt;C bool&lt;/cite&gt;
or &lt;cite&gt;C void&lt;/cite&gt; types over the &lt;cite&gt;PyObject *&lt;/cite&gt; C type. For 0.6.1 I have
observed that esp. more indicator variables make it to that stage,
generating way more efficient C code (for that indicator variable) for
those in many instances, esp. with loops, as these no longer loose type
shape information as badly as they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The, another level is when it is treated as an object, but known to be
&lt;cite&gt;int&lt;/cite&gt;, there are way more helpers used for &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt;/&lt;cite&gt;+=&lt;/cite&gt; and a whole new set
of them for comparisons, that in these cases of full or partial type
knowledge operate faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if e.g. only one type is known, this still allows to not make a
lot of tests about it, and to avoid attempted shortcuts that cannot
work. For 0.6.1 the &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;+=&lt;/cite&gt; are pretty well covered for these, but
some variants are not yet tuned to take all type knowledge advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These will be also the building block, once the C type layer picks types
like “C int or PyObject * known to be int” with indicator flags which
values are currently valid to use, then these specialized calls still
make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most attrative level, “C int” has not been reached for 0.6.1 but for
my loop example and Python3, I can say that now would be a nice time to
start it, as type shape knowledge is all there. This was totally not the
case for 0.6.0, but it seems that this step will have to be postponed to
another release, maybe 0.6.2, maybe even later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="week-of-bugfixing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Week of Bugfixing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But something that bothers me is seeing the issue tracker pile up on
actionable items, where I just have not taken action. So as announced on
Twitter already, I am having and continue to have bug fixing time. I am
acting on issues that are relatively old and easy to act on, or where I
have no hope of this happening by anybody else anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have listed some interesting examples below. But basically these are
small, relatively unimportant, yet somewhat import for some use cases
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="exec-on-filehandles"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Exec on Filehandles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when doing exec on a filehandle, Nuitka was at runtime reading the
source, then compiling it, but forgetting about the filename. This makes
things like &lt;cite&gt;inspect.getsource()&lt;/cite&gt; fail on functions from there, and ugly
tracebacks not pointing to the filename. This was one of the things
which I had understood, but not did the actual work yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pkgutil-iter-modules"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;pkgutil.iter_modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And another one, which seemed just not done, but turned out to be rather
complex, this one needs to populate a &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sys.path_importer_cache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for
imported modules, and then to report the child modules. There was no
object to carry that information, so now instances of the meta path
based importer are associated for every import.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out for Python3, my simplistic type building calling &lt;cite&gt;type&lt;/cite&gt;
manually here does not work, as &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;iter_modules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; do not
become anything but static methods ever. Needs a real type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, I had to disable it for now, because mixed packages, like the one
we do with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;multiprocessing&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;where&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;only&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;part&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;compiled&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;(the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;one&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;required)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;part&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;pure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;Python&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;disk&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;still,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;stopped&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;work.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;The&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="pre"&gt;``iter_modules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; it seems will have to cover that case too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no luck, postponing this until next week of bug fixes. Frustrating a
bit, but such is life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="when-to-release"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;When to release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still some issues that I want to get to. Specicially the
OpenGL plugins which has been research ever since, and nobody stepped
up, but it’s rather trivial. And the Tcl/Tk for Windows. People have
provided sufficient instructions for a plugin that I am going to write
this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I feel the issue tracker is clean, I will release. As a matter of
experience, it is then going to grow a lot again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally somebody has stepped up, which means a lot to me. Now to the
actual work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be very active there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-11.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-11.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #11</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2018-12-10T07:09:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-12.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #12</title>
    <updated>2019-02-08T14:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-12"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-12" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#communication-vs-coding" id="id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimization-work" id="id4"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#week-of-bugfixing" id="id5"&gt;Week of Bugfixing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#python-flag-o-and-oo" id="id6"&gt;Python flag -O and -OO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#virtualenv-vs-venv" id="id7"&gt;Virtualenv vs. venv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka" id="id8"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-organisation" id="id9"&gt;Nuitka Organisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#windows-dependencies-from-pefile" id="id10"&gt;Windows Dependencies from pefile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#tkinter-plugin" id="id11"&gt;Tkinter Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#numpy-plugin" id="id12"&gt;Numpy Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id13"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id14"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id15"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-vs-coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the holiday season I sort of neglected these postings, but there
are other fields, where I have put my focus, but I think these postings
are now going to resume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick update in a while in an eternally fluent situation, and not too
polished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the 0.6.2 optimization work has been not a lot yet. I started some
work on &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; C type and it looked good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="week-of-bugfixing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Week of Bugfixing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did this, and it turned out rather long. I continued fixing things
and finishing up open things to the point that it now is clean. I hate
to be falling behind. I am touching on a few more interesting topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-flag-o-and-oo"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Python flag -O and -OO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka was supporting &lt;cite&gt;-O&lt;/cite&gt; but doing what should only the done for &lt;cite&gt;-OO&lt;/cite&gt;
which I only learned of now. So this is going to be supported both now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="virtualenv-vs-venv"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Virtualenv vs. venv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accelerated binaries were not running with full &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sys.path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in the
virtualenv, because &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module uses &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sys.prefix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and that was not
propagated,but it now is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="google-summer-of-code-for-nuitka"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Google Summer of Code for Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the GSoC 2019 page is shaping up, the pull request to list Nuitka on
the PSF project pages has been merged. More tweaking will be needed to
get into perfect shape, and that has been my main communication time
effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally somebody had stepped up for mentor, which means a lot to me. Now
we need to see if students are willing to pick us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And because I publish this too late. Already a bunch of stundents are
showing interest and are hacking on Nuitka, which keeps me even more
busy, and makes me extremely happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="nuitka-organisation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Nuitka Organisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nuitka organisation on Github was introduced for my a while ago, and
I had transferred the ownership of the Nuitka repository to there.
Having moved the issue tracking to there, I was going more all in on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently more people have submitted PRs and with incredible quality and
willingness to support it even after merge of their PR. No dry by
contribution, but people looking to actually improve Nuitka together
with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore I welcome Orsiris and Jorj on board and am really happy about
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="windows-dependencies-from-pefile"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Windows Dependencies from pefile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Orsiris de Jong implemented a replacement for the dependency walker
based code to scan DLLs for Windows standalone using the &lt;cite&gt;pefile&lt;/cite&gt;
module, which is likely way better at this. For starters it’s
experimental in the next release, but I expect it to soon become the
default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="tkinter-plugin"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Tkinter Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Jorj X. McKie implemented a Windows Tkinter plug-in that deals with
copying of the TCL installation and integrating it with Nuitka
standalone for distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is very nice and seems to affect a lot of people using that GUI
style it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="numpy-plugin"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Numpy Plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Jorj X. McKie also implemented a NumPy plug-in that deals with the
various acceleration methods there are, e.g. MKL, Blas, I have no idea.
It copies the needed DLLs along and makes sure that &lt;cite&gt;numpy&lt;/cite&gt; stays fast
in standalone mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be very active there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-12.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-12.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #12</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2019-02-08T14:09:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-13.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka this week #13</title>
    <updated>2019-05-12T11:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-this-week-13"&gt;

&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-this-week-13" id="id2"&gt;Nuitka this week #13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#communication-vs-coding" id="id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#google-summer-of-code-2019" id="id4"&gt;Google Summer of Code 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#my-experience" id="id5"&gt;My Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#accepted-students" id="id6"&gt;Accepted Students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimization-work" id="id7"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#core-stuff" id="id8"&gt;Core Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#faster-windows-dependencies" id="id9"&gt;Faster Windows Dependencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-organisation" id="id10"&gt;Nuitka Organisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#plugin-work" id="id11"&gt;Plugin Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#opening-up" id="id12"&gt;Opening Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id13"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#help-wanted" id="id14"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#donations" id="id15"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-vs-coding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Communication vs. Coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communication was a lot more, just not these postings. Nuitka has
ventured into important realms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, active developers have joined Nuitka. Second, as a consequence of
the later, Nuitka indeed was able to participate with a insanely
powerful offering of 4 mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meant, that a lot of technical or project management debt hat to be
dealt with, and there was no time to make this kind of posting. This is
probably good news on all fronts, except that I feel they are missing,
and am glad to be able to resume them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="google-summer-of-code-2019"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Google Summer of Code 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="my-experience"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;My Experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the most crazy ride and fun. Became the admin of an active
sub-organisation under the PSF umbrella for GSoC 2019. So shortly after
the announcement of the project lists, students flooded in, and starting
working on things right away as early as February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were working hard to prove themselves and get to know Nuitka,
asking many questions, with us having lots of email interviews, and even
a lot of video calls, where I personally talked to people about ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happened simultaneously to more experienced developers joining the
project as well, making very important contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This basically meant, that many days 90%-100% of my Nuitka time was for
communication or working off technical debts I knew there were, or for
preparing things, I want to have with multiple people working on the
code base. This will be detailed in other sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="accepted-students"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Accepted Students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this has paid of in that we now have 2 really good students to
work on 2 Nuitka projects over the summer. Let’s welcome Batakrishna and
Tommy in separate posts. They will introduce themselves and what they
are going to do shortly, in separate posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets just say, this is fantastic news. We had so many good applications
and its a shame, but we knew right away, not everybody who deserved it
could be picked. But this is going to be a good chance for us to get to
be open and welcoming to new people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Optimization Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="core-stuff"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Core Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the 0.6.3 release (btw. on Windows, be sure to use the 0.6.3.1
hotfix), which was made as a consolidation effort to get the good work
of mostly other people out, didn’t contain much optimization work for
the core, as that is still my thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this changed a lot. An idea that came to my mind for how to do
the massive amounts of specialized helpers needed beyond &lt;cite&gt;+&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;+=&lt;/cite&gt;,
with which I had started for prior releases. And that is to use Jinja2
based templates for C, to generate the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an important idea. Took a while, but soon the manual code for
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; was already replaced with generated code, fixing a few bugs by the
way, and from there, the generation was expanded to cover &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, support for the 3 (!) different kinds of additions
(&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;TrueDiv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;FloorDir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; as well as Python2 default division,
dubbed &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;OldDiv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in Nuitka was added along with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; were done first, is that they have special
treatment for sequences, using &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sq_concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;sq_repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, where
the other operations will be more straightforward, e.g. &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;nb_subtract&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
(&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;) has a lot types supporting it and that makes those the easy
cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am saving a deeper explanation of 3 things we will need for the next
time. Basically we need optimization of these things at compile time,
and that is getting there, and code to use in the backend, and that is
getting there, and a third thing, that is to use optimization knowledge
to apply the special code as much as possible, and that is not yet fully
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="faster-windows-dependencies"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Faster Windows Dependencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to excite Windows users. After Orsiris de Jong had done a
replacement for dependency walker that is faster, this had remained in
an experimental status, just due to lack of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently however, I felt there is more time, after GSoC student
selection has happened, and that I could finally work a bit on open
issues like this. And when I wrote a dedicated tool, to analyse
dependences with either technology to compare the results, I found that
dendency walker founds a lot more things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a turn down, but turns out, nothing it finds is stuff that
should not be on the white list. In fact, it’s all core Windows things,
and from the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;System32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; folder. That made me question, why we take
anything from there (except maybe &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;PythonXY.dll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;) at all, and after
that change the performance changed dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dependency walker now finishes a file in milliseconds. Actually the
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pefile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is now slow (surely it ought to be compiled), and takes some
seconds, for a file. That is amazing, and has lead to me to remove the
parallel usage, and since &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pefile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; allows for perfect caching, and is
Free Software, we will probably keep it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will address a widespread complaint of many Windows users of the
standalone mode. This is now a relatively unnoticable part of the
overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I need to finish off some remaining problems with it, before
putting it out in the wild. Getting this into a release will solve many
newcomer issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="nuitka-organisation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Nuitka Organisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esp. for Google Summer of Code, Nuitka has sought and found mentors,
some of which are highly experienced for the task. I will let them
decide and write their own introduction, but I feel really blessed by
them helping me out in my desperate calls for help. Without them,
neither could Nuitka participate, nor could it even overachieve as much
as it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore I welcomed Kamran and Vaibhav into the organisation and they
are excited to work the the 2 accepted students, that are also added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="plugin-work"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Plugin Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;jorj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; branch there is a lot of work from Jorj that aims at
adding support for more of the beasty stuff with hidden dependency and
plugin needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is also working at run time tracing of your program to be translated
to automatic imports of just that. I am going to highlight this later,
once I manage to cherry-pick the release ready parts from it for the
next release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this definitely awesome stuff, and going to make Nuitka very easy to
use for some people, even with stranger software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="opening-up"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Opening Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a teaser. But we did so much work for the 0.6.3 release to
make sure information is there, and things are accessible and changeable
by everyone, or even the pre-commit hook that I am very proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I shall save this for next week, otherwise it will be too much new
information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be active there, although often I fall prey to of not
wanting to talk about unfinished things. On Twitter of all things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Follow &amp;#64;kayhayen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets not forget, having followers make me happy. So do re-tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding Twitter more prominently to the web site is something that is
also going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="help-wanted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: INFO/1 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;/home/runner/work/Nuitka-website/Nuitka-website/doc/posts/nuitka-this-week-13.rst&lt;/span&gt;, line 7); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id1"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplicate implicit target name: “help wanted”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, I am tagging issues &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kayhayen/Nuitka/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22help+wanted%22"&gt;help wanted&lt;/a&gt;
and there is a bunch, and very likely at least one &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka definitely needs more people to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Donations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, but cannot spend the time, please consider to
donate to Nuitka, and go here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;Donate to Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-this-week-13.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Nuitka this week #13</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="NTW" label="NTW"/>
    <published>2019-05-12T11:07:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
