<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posts tagged Windows</title>
  <updated>2022-02-12T18:04:05.949358+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/tag/windows/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/letting-go-of-c11.html</id>
    <title>Letting go of C++11</title>
    <updated>2012-10-27T08:59:07+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How Nuitka came to use C++11 and then stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="letting-go-of-c-11"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about Nuitka the Python compiler started out using C++0x
which is now C++11, and then chose to stop it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="in-the-beginning"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In the Beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very early on, when I considered how to generate code from the node
tree, in a way, that mistakes should practically be impossible to make,
I made the fundamental decision, that every Python expression, which
produces temporary variables, should become an expression in the
generated code too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is my choice, I think it keeps code generation more simple, and
easier to understand. There may come a separate post about how that
played out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That decision meant some trouble. Certain things were not easy, but
generally, it was achievable for g++ relatively quickly, and then lots
of helper functions would be needed. Think of &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;MAKE_TUPLE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;MAKE_DICT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, but also other stuff needed that. Calling a Python
built-in with variable number of parameters e.g. could be implemented
that way easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other nice things were &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;enum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; classes, and generally good stuff. It
was really quick to get Nuitka code generation off the ground this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reality-strikes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reality Strikes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, as time went on, I found that the order of evaluation was
becoming an issue. It became apparent that for more and more things, I
needed to reverse it, so it works. Porting to ARM, it then became clear,
that it needs to be the other way around for that platform. And checking
out clang, which is also a C++11 compiler, I noticed, this one yet uses
a different one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for normal functions, I found a solution that involves the
pre-processor to reverse or not, &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; function definition and call
sites, and then it is already correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This of course, doesn’t work for C++11 variadic functions. So, there
came a point, where I had to realize, that each of its uses was more or
less causing evaluation order bugs. So that most of their uses were
already removed. And so I basically knew they couldn’t stay that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-features"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, things I initially assumed, e.g. that lambda functions of C++11
may prove useful, or even “auto”, didn’t turn out to be true. There
seemingly is a wealth of new features, besides variadic templates that I
didn’t see how Nuitka would benefit from it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="new-wishes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Wishes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, at Europython, I realized, that Android is still stuck with
g++-4.4 and as such, that an important target platform will be
unavailable to me. This platform will become even more important, as I
intend to buy an device now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="biting-it"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biting it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what I did, was to remove all variadic functions and instead generate
code for them as necessary. I just need to trace the used argument
counts, and then provide those, simple enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, other things like deleted copy constructors, and so on, I had to
give up on these a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This change was probably suited to remove subtle evaluation order
problems, although I don’t recall seeing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-present"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Present&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current stable release still requires C++11, but the next release
will work on g++-4.4 and compiles fine with MSVC from Visual Studio
2008, although at this time, there is still the issue of generators not
working yet, but I believe that ought to be solvable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new requirement is only C++03, which means, there is a good chance
that supporting Android will become feasible. I know there is interest
from App developers, because there, even the relatively unimportant 2x
speedup, that Nuitka might give for some code, may matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that is a detour, I have taken, expanding the base of Nuitka even
further. I felt, this was important enough to write down the history
part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/letting-go-of-c11.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>How Nuitka came to use C++11 and then stop it.</summary>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Windows" label="Windows"/>
    <category term="Android" label="Android"/>
    <published>2012-10-27T08:59:07+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/support-for-portable-standalone-programs.html</id>
    <title>Support for portable (standalone) programs</title>
    <updated>2013-04-07T13:52:44+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="support-for-portable-standalone-programs"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about a feature often requested, but so far not available
feature of Nuitka. Please see the page &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;“What is Nuitka?”&lt;/a&gt; for clarification of what it is now and what it
wants to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In forums, and in Google, people are looking at a Python compiler, also
as a way of deployment. It should offer what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.py2exe.org/"&gt;py2exe&lt;/a&gt; does, allow installation independent of
Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for a long time it didn’t. But thanks to recent contributions,
it’s upcoming for the next release, Nuitka 0.4.3, and it’s in the
current pre-releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works by adding &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--portable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to the command line. So this should
work for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight-bash notranslate"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;nuitka-python --recurse-all --portable your-program.py
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, it will create a folder “_python” with DLLs, and
“_python.zip” with standard library modules used along to the
“your-program.exe”. Copy these to another machine, without a Python
installation, and it will (should) work. Making that statement fully
true may need refinements, as some DLL dependencies might not be defined
yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may improve it in the future to meld everything into one
executable for even easier deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are more than welcome to experiment with it. To do so, download
Nuitka from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/download.html"&gt;download page&lt;/a&gt; and give it a
roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Nuitka is not about replacing “py2exe” primarily, it’s
only a side effect of what we do. Our major goal is of course to
accelerate Python, but surely nobody minds achieving the two things
at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while the post is labeled “Windows”, this feature also works for
Linux at least too. It’s just that the lack of Python installations on
client systems is far more widespread on this platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, as this is from a contributor, it’s another sign of Nuitka
gaining adoption for real usage. My personal “py2exe” experience is
practically not existing, I have never used it. And I will only merge
the improvements into the Nuitka project as provided by others. My focus
for the time to come is of course the compile time and run time
optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/support-for-portable-standalone-programs.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>This post is about a feature often requested, but so far not available
feature of Nuitka. Please see the page “What is Nuitka?” for clarification of what it is now and what it
wants to be.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Windows" label="Windows"/>
    <published>2013-04-07T13:52:44+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/support-for-msvc-upcoming.html</id>
    <title>Support for MSVC upcoming</title>
    <updated>2013-04-10T20:30:11+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="support-for-msvc-upcoming"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news are lately coming in high density, although I barely have
the opportunity to work on Nuitka. Check the page &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;What is Nuitka?&lt;/a&gt; for clarification of what it is now and what it
wants to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems my &lt;a class="reference external" href="nuitka-needs-you-a-call-for-help.html"&gt;recent call for help&lt;/a&gt; was at least partially
effective. One the major points has been addressed. In the next release,
Visual Studio 2008 and 2010 will both work for Nuitka, right now it’s
only in git develop branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is really nice, as it will make Nuitka on Windows a whole lot more
accessible. Combine that with &lt;a class="reference external" href="support-for-portable-standalone-programs.html"&gt;portable support&lt;/a&gt; and it’s up to solving
problems with distributing on Windows it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other two things listed there have received no feedback yet. So if
you want to help with those, feel free to do so. Nuitka needs you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/support-for-msvc-upcoming.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>The good news are lately coming in high density, although I barely have
the opportunity to work on Nuitka. Check the page What is Nuitka? for clarification of what it is now and what it
wants to be.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="Windows" label="Windows"/>
    <published>2013-04-10T20:30:11+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-standalone-mode-is-work-in-progress.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Standalone Mode is Work in Progress</title>
    <updated>2013-12-27T10:48:22+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-standalone-mode-is-work-in-progress"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you who turn to my easy to use, highly compatible Python
compiler &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://nuitka.net"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;, do this mostly because they
seek to solve the deployment problem that Python suffers from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be this, because you want to use a newer Python2.7 on RHEL5 without
installing anything at all there. Or because Windows is difficult to
tackle otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the longest time, Nuitka had not offered anything in this domain,
focusing solely on being an accelerator. Lately, I have taken up the
challenge and polished initial solutions submitted by contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first showed up in the 0.4.7 release, but turned out relatively
weak. While first examples were working on Linux, it was not working at
all on Windows (anymore). And basically there was a huge lack of tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually I didn’t mean for it to be released with that feature, but as
parts of it seemed to work, I did so. But truth to be sad, that feature
is not nearly as polished in that release as you would like it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In current &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/download.html"&gt;development releases&lt;/a&gt;, of what is going to become
0.5.0 really soon now, it’s much better already. More things actually
work. But it appears, there will be more ground to cover, and this is a
lot of stuff to sort out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is mostly about asking you two things. Give that development
release a try and report issues you have with it. And help me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And have patience. I am developing Nuitka as an accelerator on a “no
known bugs” basis. That means, once I know of a bug, I will fix it. OK,
some issues in fact take longer, but then it really is not important at
all, but difficult at the time. For standalone mode, I can’t do it that
way, or I would have to neglect the acceleration parts, which I totally
don’t want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because while you maybe are only interested in a packaging solution,
many others would like to have that orders of magnitude speedup that I
have been aiming for and that feels near now. This is about making
Python a viable language for more uses than it currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do it in the first place. For one, I am hoping that it helps
people to not turn away from Python. And second, and more important, I
am hoping that by making it more useful, more people will join me. (Oh,
and thirdly, it’s also a nice puzzle to solve. I seem to enjoy that.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately both modes will be needed, standalone, and acceleration. And
it seems like I am working to provide both. For standalone, more often,
than seeking to avoid bugs as far as possible, I am going to rely on
your participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So join Nuitka. Now. &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/download.html"&gt;Download from here&lt;/a&gt;. Join the mailing list (since
closed). And help if you can. And yes you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-standalone-mode-is-work-in-progress.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Many of you who turn to my easy to use, highly compatible Python
compiler Nuitka, do this mostly because they
seek to solve the deployment problem that Python suffers from.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="Windows" label="Windows"/>
    <published>2013-12-27T10:48:22+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
