<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://nuitka.net</id>
  <title>Nuitka Blog - Posts tagged europython</title>
  <updated>2022-02-15T17:29:19.734050+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net"/>
  <link href="https://nuitka.net/blog/tag/europython/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.23">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/going-to-europython-2013.html</id>
    <title>Going to Europython 2013</title>
    <updated>2013-04-16T09:58:34+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="going-to-europython-2013"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to the wonderful city of Florence, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ep2013.europython.eu/"&gt;Europython 2013&lt;/a&gt; and make a presentation there. This
time, I am not introducing Nuitka anymore, I did that in 2012, this
time, I will try and dive into static optimization and try to convey the
message why I believe it is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#going-to-europython-2013" id="id1"&gt;Going to Europython 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#things-to-talk-about" id="id2"&gt;Things to talk about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#status" id="id3"&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#last-years-questions" id="id4"&gt;Last years questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#builtins" id="id5"&gt;Builtins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#debugger-pdb" id="id6"&gt;Debugger - pdb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#threading" id="id7"&gt;Threading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#c-to-python-gaps" id="id8"&gt;C++ to Python gaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance" id="id9"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#demos" id="id10"&gt;Demos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#future-work" id="id11"&gt;Future Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#ssa" id="id12"&gt;SSA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#compiled-modules" id="id13"&gt;Compiled Modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#compiled-locals" id="id14"&gt;Compiled Locals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#whole-program-analysis" id="id15"&gt;Whole Program Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#perspective" id="id16"&gt;Perspective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#funding" id="id17"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#final-picture" id="id18"&gt;Final Picture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#final-words" id="id19"&gt;Final Words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="things-to-talk-about"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;Things to talk about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="status"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only briefly this time, since I will be able to say that all current
Python versions are fully supported (&lt;a class="reference external" href="nuitka-needs-you-a-call-for-help.html"&gt;surely if you help me with
Python3.3 yield from&lt;/a&gt;), all
major platforms now. One important milestone has been reached meanwhile,
and work on far reaching compile time optimizations is happening. As
this should be quite obvious stuff, I am going to keep that short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would like to get done until then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Win64&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One remaining area of work to achieve Win64 support, which is almost
complete. I epxect one of the next releases to support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Threading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course there is threading, which was the one real major
weakness present last time, which appears only short of pronouncing
break-through. At least one user is using Nuitka with many threads
operationally already. I just have to re-activate the thread using
tests CPython that I disabled. Seems I only have to convince myself
of it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it’s not totally a priority right now, one of the next releases
will support it, likely before the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as you see. Completion all around is there or at least in sight.
Kind of worked on this nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="last-years-questions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Last years questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;section id="builtins"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Builtins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, writing to built-ins, what will/did happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing builtins can be done in two ways. One is to set the value on
the module level, which is something that has always worked. The other
is writing to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;builtins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something that is OK for Nuitka in some cases (&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;__import__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; ) and handled by it at run time. And it’s not effective in
others (&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good news is that we got contributed a “compiled built-ins” code, where
we now will be able to see such writes. Now it’s only used to not check
every time for changes, but to know them (pull vs. push). But we will
also use it and trigger &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;RuntimeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; exceptions for things we cannot
handle when we only learn of it at run time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other element to address is, it of course whole program analysis.
When Nuitka sees the write to &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;builtins.str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, it may very well
consider it. The distinction between initial and current builtin values,
and the optimization of it, that will be interesting to cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently Nuitka does nothing of this, but it will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="debugger-pdb"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Debugger - pdb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiled binaries work the same as the normal Python code. So you
will be able to simply use &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; on it instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interacting with &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is not &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; out of reach, but kind of
pointless mostly, unless you need to attach to long running operational
programs. For now that use case is not supported though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="threading"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Threading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a whole lot about threading. Also thanks to the kind people of
Stackless Python, who explained things to me. I am still amazed at how
little I did know of these things, and still went so far. In my
industry, threads are considered not allowed, and I personally don’t
like them either, so my experience was non-existing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the mean time, I managed to come up with ideas that appear to
work, and if I implement the full design, it will even be more efficient
than anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="c-to-python-gaps"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;C++ to Python gaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider all of these more or less solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well maybe except recently arose issues with MSVC for “function calls”.
It appears that compiler highlights a weakness in one of my approaches.
Nuitka so far only changed the order of declaration and call arguments
around, which is kind of transparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But MSVC actively takes liberty to calculate function arguments as it
sees fit. The fix for it, is now totally different and should be highly
portable and even compliant to C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still slow exceptions. I would like to avoid raising C++
exceptions in the future, because they are so slow (Python exceptions
are much faster).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And diagrams, I would like to have a whole lot more of these. Since I
dropped speedcenter, I am making actual progress there. I hope to have
enough to show at the conference, where the actual strength and weakness
currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I am getting closer to pronouncing Nuitka useful. I surely
believe, I need to answer the performance question in larger detail. And
of course, I need now a better idea, what impact measures have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as this is a lot of work, I doubt that I will be all that perfect by
then, my goal is to have a comparison with Shedskin. No matter how
unfair it is (Shedskin does only a small subset of Python), it’s the
most useful comparison in my eyes, as where Shedskin makes static type
analysis, Nuitka also should do it, only hampered by guards at maximum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="demos"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Demos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk with start out with demonstration of Nuitka, something simple
first, and then Mercurial as a more complex example, and then its test
suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I will show portable binaries. It seems to work quite nicely.
Generally I expect to start out with demos, and explain from there,
instead of having a demo only at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it all works out, this time, they will be prepared with
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;recordmydesktop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; so I can publish them separately too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="future-work"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Future Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally the talk will be more directed at the future, although this is
kind of a dark area now. That’s its nature I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="ssa"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;SSA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk will also be largely built SSA (static single assignment) and
how it applies to Python. What everybody means, when they say “Python is
too dynamic (to be statically compiled)” is that Python values may
escape to unknown code that changes them very often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have to talk about that, and how get out of that trap, basically
guards, much like PyPy does it too. Escaped values and strange code are
only one option of things to occur. Having code for both cases, sounds
possible. I will talk about how to decide, which branches we shall have
and which not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="compiled-modules"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Compiled Modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I believe with “compiled modules” potentially already in place, we
can achieve very cheap guards in most cases. I can at least explain, why
guards can be relatively cheap, where we need them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am kind of bugged by that idea. It kind of means to revisit an older
milestone, but now an idea has surfaced, that I previously didn’t have,
and that I am very curious to learn the benefit of. Very quick &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;
safe module variabls, are very tempting to have, and definitely make a
difference for the Nuitka design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="compiled-locals"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;Compiled Locals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows, we might even have a “compiled locals” as well, which as a
side effect, also allows total interactivity with the most absurd codes.
So far, each local variable is a C++ object, and as this is compiled,
and very fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the frame locals is not in sync with it. Were it a special object,
it could try and interact with these when control escapes to code that
we don’t know if it might use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="whole-program-analysis"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Whole Program Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big words. Can Nuitka avoid module objects entirely. Can it inline
functions, specialize them according to the only types used (think
including &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;os.path.dirname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in the binary, but with the constraint
that it only need to work on string objects as input, because the
program is known to use it any different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="perspective"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Perspective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time, I spent a lot of time on justification, “why a new project?”,
“why not work with the others?”, what goals do I have that others do
not. Giving examples of how code generation works. Generally to give
people an idea of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this out of the way, I can now focus on inclusion, and success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="funding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, well yes, this time I may not have to pay for it all by myself.
Last time I spent close to 1000 Euros for the trip (ticket to enter,
hotel, flight, food), because I am &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;accepting donations&lt;/a&gt; for this specific reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a strange reason, I devote substantial amounts of time to the
project, only to put it under the most liberal license. It’s probably
fair to allow people to &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;make donations&lt;/a&gt; if
they feel they want to further the project, but don’t know how. Or if
they just consider it too important for me to loose interest. That kind
of feels unlikely though. Too much fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="final-picture"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Final Picture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lets have an image I made during Europython 2012 in the city of
Florence. It shows what a vibrant place this town is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../../_images/europython-2012-07-img6319.jpg" src="../../_images/europython-2012-07-img6319.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Florence is a place full of kind people. The mood not only of the
conference, but the whole city is very open minded and helpful. It was
very easy to get adopted by strangers to their party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="final-words"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id19"&gt;Final Words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to meeting the friends I made there last time, and
new friends. I kind of a great time there last time, one of these “times
of my life”. Even if the reception was not always as warm as I had
deserved. I remember laughing a lot, learning a lot. And making unique
experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/going-to-europython-2013.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>I am going to the wonderful city of Florence, and Europython 2013 and make a presentation there. This
time, I am not introducing Nuitka anymore, I did that in 2012, this
time, I will try and dive into static optimization and try to convey the
message why I believe it is possible.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2013-04-16T09:58:34+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html</id>
    <title>My Europython 2013 report</title>
    <updated>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="my-europython-2013-report"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;Python compiler Nuitka&lt;/a&gt;.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BDjXZY_8d58" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talk went really well. I believe one can clearly see that I felt
really good and at ease. The state presented is very good and progress -
there was a lot, so that was great. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2013.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of the talk may also be
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it definitely raised a lot of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last years talk is also there. You can (maybe) see that I was 20kg more
weight then, and also &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more excited, at least initially.
Background: I was surprised then that Guido van Rossum was attending the
talk, plus I was kind of not in the state of this year, the confidence
that people should believe, that things will work after that, was not
yet there. I knew it, but standing in front of a croud and saying, look
I am attempting what you consider impossible, or even have failed at, is
not easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video_wrapper" style=""&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="true" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZDHkla5rllg" style="border: 0; height: 345px; width: 560px"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pr/Nuitka-Presentation-PyCON-EU-2012.pdf"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; of that talk which may
also be interesting, but of course are outdated somewhat now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="years-make-differences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Years make differences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, the progress happened since 2012 made a difference. Nuitka has
proven things. Let’s see what this year does to it. I would hope for
real type inference optimization and portable mode to be there next
year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider that is the a &lt;em&gt;spare time effort&lt;/em&gt;. Lots of people lauded it for
the out of the box experience, and how it just works. That’s right. I
put a lot of focus on stability, correctness, and ease of use. In fact,
since my return, I have mostly worked on the feedback I got in that
domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the relatively small amount of time I can invest (outside of
holidays), it’s make very fast progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="out-of-the-box-thinking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Out of the box thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback during the conference was great. While Nuitka is not yet
seeing a lot of users, and not as many contributions or donations as I
would hope for, but that’s kind of expected with my out of the box
thinking there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few people at Europython really need a Python compiler. The most
important exception are scientific people, doing number crunching. And I
made some interesting contacts there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my return, I have been receiving a bunch of bug reports. Some of
which were unfortunately regressions of 0.4.4, and these got fixed in
two hotfix releases. Currently 0.4.4.2 is released, and contains a huge
amount of fixes, mostly stuff found by the surge new users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I deserved that, having said that I didn’t have to do hotfixes for a
while now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="florence"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Florence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a lovely place, and so lovely people. It’s a tourist place, true,
but it’s very open minded. The food is extremely good. And going from
the conference hotel straight over to the river to meet up and have a
few beers was very comfortable for after-conference stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have been there 2 times, and the conference even 3 times,
it’s moving on, to Berlin, which I sort of regret. Knowing the place
somewhat definitely is an advantage by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="python-revolution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that came to my mind during the conference, witnessing the
large amount of non-satisfaction, was that the community is fed up with
the leadership. Questioned about lack of Python3 adoption, a PSF guy in
his presentation said they were 3 years into a 5 years plan, and got
interrupted by laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be about time, somebody actually gets up, removes the GIL and has
a Python2.8 that is compatible. Obviously that’s much more useful. It
could be a Python3.x with compatibility names of modules, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
statement, and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict.iteritems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; added, probably also making some of
the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; mess more harmless, and providing &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering that I have in fact been playing with the idea of forking
CPython top versions, to add things, that would allow Nuitka to work
better with it, that could be a staging ground, where such changes are
nurtured. On the other hand, Nuitka is too irrelevant yet to drive this,
and it would detract me away from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="gains"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Nuitka got a lot more exposure. And one guy watching the talk even
created a really &lt;a class="reference external" href="/_static/Nuitka-Logo-Symbol.svg"&gt;nice logo&lt;/a&gt; for
it. I will make it a separate announcement though, and the next release
is going to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the aftermath, there were much bug useful reports. And new ideas.
And reinforcement that what I am doing is actually useful to some people
already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="donations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Donations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My travel to Florence was in part funded by donations. Thanks a lot to
all of you who have given, and who would like to also &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;make a donation&lt;/a&gt;. Should I receive sufficient donations, I
intend to go to FOSDEM 2014 as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to Berlin will be a bit cheaper this time around, as I can travel
there via train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Europython 2012 and 2013 both are among the times of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/my-europython-2013-report.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Back from Europython 2013 in Florence for a while now. I had a
presentation about my Python compiler Nuitka.
You can watch the Video on Youtube. I believe it’s absolutely worth your
time. I was not doing a lot of “why” at all now, only “what”, and demo
times, and answering questions:</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <category term="presentation" label="presentation"/>
    <category term="video" label="video"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2013-08-15T08:15:17+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/not-going-to-fosdem-2014.html</id>
    <title>Not going to FOSDEM 2014</title>
    <updated>2014-01-18T20:48:53+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="not-going-to-fosdem-2014"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I submitted a talk for FOSDEM “Python has a compiler now”. And it
didn’t get accepted. Quite a surprise to me, but likely mostly logical.
These are the accepted talks (link since became unavailable) and well,
it surely didn’t fit in, right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intent was to introduce &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/overview.html"&gt;Nuitka&lt;/a&gt; to the
larger community. Not going to happen now, but maybe next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly triggered by the rejection, I am questioning Europython 2014 in
Berlin as a useful destination too. To me it seems, that code writing is
the best way to create the community at this time anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/not-going-to-fosdem-2014.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>So I submitted a talk for FOSDEM “Python has a compiler now”. And it
didn’t get accepted. Quite a surprise to me, but likely mostly logical.
These are the accepted talks (link since became unavailable) and well,
it surely didn’t fit in, right.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <category term="conference" label="conference"/>
    <published>2014-01-18T20:48:53+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-progress-winter-2015.html</id>
    <title>Nuitka Progress in 2015</title>
    <updated>2016-01-29T08:08:54+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Kay Hayen</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="nuitka-progress-in-2015"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For quite a bit, there have been no status posts, not for lack of news,
but a lot has happened indeed. I just seem to post a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more to the
mailing list than I do here. Especially about unfinished stuff, which is
essentially for a project like Nuitka everything that’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I previously said, I am shy to make public postings about
unfinished stuff and that’s going to continue. But I am breaking it, to
keep you up to date with where Nuitka has been going lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with release focuses, I have been making some actual changes that I
think are worth talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="contents topic" id="contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#nuitka-progress-in-2015" id="id1"&gt;Nuitka Progress in 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#ssa-single-state-assignment-form" id="id2"&gt;SSA (Single State Assignment Form)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#function-inlining" id="id3"&gt;Function Inlining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#scalability" id="id4"&gt;Scalability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#parameter-parsing" id="id5"&gt;Parameter Parsing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#variable-error-messages" id="id6"&gt;Variable Error Messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#code-objects" id="id7"&gt;Code Objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#optimization" id="id8"&gt;Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#compatibility" id="id9"&gt;Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#performance" id="id10"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#graphs-and-benchmarks" id="id11"&gt;Graphs and Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#standalone" id="id12"&gt;Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#other-stuff" id="id13"&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#europython-2015" id="id14"&gt;EuroPython 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#funding" id="id15"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#collaborators" id="id16"&gt;Collaborators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#videos" id="id17"&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#twitter" id="id18"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#future" id="id19"&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#release-focus" id="id20"&gt;Release Focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#summary" id="id21"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="ssa-single-state-assignment-form"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;SSA (Single State Assignment Form)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SSA using release has been made last summer. Recent releases have
lifted more and more restrictions on where and now it is applied and
made sure the internal status is consistent and true. And that trend is
going to continue even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For shared variables (closure variables and module variables), Nuitka is
still too conservative to make optimization. Code does annotate value
escapes, but it’s not yet trusting it. The next releases will focus on
lifting that kind of restriction, and for quality of result, that will
mean making a huge jump ahead once that works, so module variables used
locally a lot will become even faster to use then and subject to static
optimization too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="function-inlining"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Function Inlining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When doing my talk to EuroPython 2015, I was demoing it that, and
indeed, what a break through. The circumstances under which it is done
are still far too limited though. Essentially that ability is there, but
will not normally be noticeable yet due to other optimization, e.g.
functions are most often module variables and not local to the using
function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More code generation improvements will be needed to be able to inline
functions that might raise an exception. Also the “cost” of inlining a
function is also very much an unsolved issue. It will become the focus
again, once the SSA use as indicated above expands to module variables,
as then inlining other things than local functions will be possible too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is a lot of things to do for this to really make a difference
to your programs. But it’s still great to have that part solved so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="scalability"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;Scalability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="parameter-parsing"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Parameter Parsing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent releases have replaced some of the oldest code of Nuitka, the one
that generated special argument parsing for each function individually,
now replaced with generic code, that surprisingly is often even faster,
although quick entry points were tough to beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gives the C backend compiler a much easier time. Previously 3 C
functions were created per Python level function, two of which could get
really big with many arguments, and these are no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="variable-error-messages"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id6"&gt;Variable Error Messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something similar was going on with variable error messages. Each had
their exception value pre-computed and created at module load time. Most
of these are of course unused. This has been replaced with code that
generates it on the fly, resulting in a lot less constants code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="code-objects"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id7"&gt;Code Objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And another thing was to look after code objects, of which there often
were two for each Python level function. The one used or the frame
during run time and the one used in the function object, differered
often, sometimes by small things like flags or local variable names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That of course was just the result of not passing that along, but
created cached objects with hopefully the same options, but that not
being true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolving that, and sharing the code object used for creation and then
the frame is gives less complex C code too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id8"&gt;Optimization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scalability of Nuitka also depends much on generated code size. With
the optimization become more clever, less code is generated, and that
trend will continue as more structural optimization are applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time e.g. an exception is identified to not happen, this removes
the corresponding error exits from the C code, which then makes it
easier for the C compiler. Also more specialized code as we now have or
dictionaries, is often less complex to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="compatibility"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id9"&gt;Compatibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important things have happened here. Full compatibility mode is planned
to not be the default anymore in upcoming releases, but that will only
mean to not be stupid compatible, but to e.g. have more complete error
messages than CPython, more correct line numbers, or for version
differences, the best Python version behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stable release has full support for Python 3.5, including the new
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;async&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;await&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; functions. So recent releases can pronounce it
as fully supported which was quite a feat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure, if you can fully appreciate the catch up game needed to
play here. CPython clearly implements a lot of features, that I have to
emulate too. That’s going to repeat for every major release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that the function type of Nuitka is now specialized to
the generators and classes, and that was a massive cleanup of its core
that was due anyway. The generators have no more their own function
creation stuff and that has been helpful with a lot of other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another focus driven from Python3, is to get ahead with type shape
tracing and type inference of dictionary, and value tracing. To fully
support Python3 classes, we need to work on something that is a
dictionary a-like, and that will only ever be efficient if we have that.
Good news is that the next release is making progress there too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id10"&gt;Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="graphs-and-benchmarks"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id11"&gt;Graphs and Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also presented this weak point to EuroPython 2015 and my plan on how
to resolve it. Unfortunately, nothing really happened here. My plan is
still to use what the PyPy people have developed as vmprof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that is not progressing, and I could need help with that definitely.
Get in contact if you think you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="standalone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id12"&gt;Standalone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standalone mode of Nuitka was pretty good, and continued to improve
further, but I don’t care much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-stuff"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id13"&gt;Other Stuff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="europython-2015"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id14"&gt;EuroPython 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a blast. Meeting people who knew Nuitka but not me was a
regular occurrence. And many people well appreciate my work. It felt
much different than the years before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to present Nuitka’s function in-lining indeed there, and this
high goal that I set myself, quite impressed people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I made many new contacts, largely with the scientific community. I
hope to find work with data scientists in the coming years. More amd
more it looks like my day job should be closer to Nuitka and my
expertise in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="funding"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id15"&gt;Funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka receives the occasional &lt;a class="reference external" href="/pages/donations.html"&gt;donation&lt;/a&gt; and those make me very happy.
As there is no support from organization like the PSF, I am all on my
own there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I want to travel to Europython 2016. It would be sweet if
aside of my free time it wouldn’t also cost me money. So please consider
donating some more, as these kind of events are really helpul to Nuitka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="collaborators"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id16"&gt;Collaborators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuitka is making more and more break through progress. And you can be a
part of it. Now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can join and should do so now, just &lt;a class="reference external" href="/doc/user-manual.html#join-nuitka"&gt;follow this link&lt;/a&gt; or become part of
the mailing list (since closed) and help me there with request I make,
e.g. review posts of mine, test out things, pick up small jobs, answer
questions of newcomers, you know the drill probably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="videos"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id17"&gt;Videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Youtube channel of mine with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLKO58t9ADuF6o_Dcmve1DXpUkUEEVvDux"&gt;all the videos of Nuitka so far&lt;/a&gt;
and I have been preparing myself with proper equipment to make Videos of
Nuitka, but so far nothing has come out of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do however really want to change that. Let’s see if it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="twitter"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id18"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have started to use &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/kayhayen"&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; on occasions. You are welcome to follow
me there. I will highlight interesting stuff there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id19"&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there is multiple things going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type Inference&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With SSA in place, Nuitka starts to recognize types, and treat things
that work something assigned from &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; built-in with
special nodes and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s going to be a lot of work. For &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; there
are very important use cases, where the code can be much better. But
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the hardest case, and to get the structure of shape
tracing right, we are going there first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shape Analyisis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan for types, is not to use them, but the more general shapes,
things that will be more prevalent than actual type information in a
program. In fact the precise knowledge will be rare, but more often,
we will just have a set of operations performed on a variable, and be
able to guess from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape analysis will begin though with concrete types like &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.
The reason is that some re-formulations like Python3 classes should
not use locals, but dictionary accesses throughout for full
compatibility. Tracing that correctly to be effectively the same code
quality will allow to make that change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plug-ins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I wish I could have shown at EuroPython was plug-ins to
Nuitka. It has become more complete, and some demo plug-ins for say
Qt plugins or multiprocessing, are starting to work, but it’s not
progressing recently. The API will need work and of course
documentation. Hope is for this to expand Nuitka’s reach and appeal
to get more contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be sweet, if there were any takers, aiming to complete these
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nested frames&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One result of in-lining will be nested frames still present for
exceptions to be properly annotated, or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;locals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; giving different
sets of locals and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cleanup of these will be needed for code generation and SSA to
be able to attach variables to some sort of container, and for a
function to be able to reference different sets of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know, if you are willing to help. I really need that help to make
things happen faster. Nuitka will become more and more important only.
And with your help, things will be there sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="release-focus"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id20"&gt;Release Focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I have started recently, is to make changes to Nuitka focused
to just one goal, and to only deal with the rare bug in other fields,
but not much else at all. So instead of across the board improvements in
just about everything, I have e.g. in the last release added type
inference for dictionaries and special nodes and their code generation
for dictionary operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This progresses Nuitka in one field. And the next release then e.g. will
only focus on making the performance comparison tool, and not continue
much in other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way, more “flow” is possible and more visible progress too. As an
example of this, these are the focuses of last releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full Python 3.5 on a clean base with generators redone so that
coroutines fit in nicely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scalability of C compilation with argument parsing redone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next release soon: Shape analysis of subscript usages and
optimization to exact dictionaries&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next release thereafter: Comparison benchmarking (vmprof, resolving C
level function identifiers easier)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other focuses will also happen, but that’s too far ahead. Mostly like
some usability improvements will be the focus of a release some day.
Focus is for things that are too complex to attack as a side project,
and therefore never happen although surely possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging into Python3.5 coroutines and their semantics was hard enough,
and the structural changes needed to integrate them properly with not
too much special casing, but rather removing existing special cases
(generator functions) was just too much work to ever happen while also
doing other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id21"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am very excited about Nuitka. It feels like the puzzle is coming
together finally, with type inference becoming a real thing. And should
dictionaries be sorted out, the real important types, say &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for
scientific use cases, or &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; for others, will be easy to
make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, and then harder import association (knowing what other
modules are), and module level SSA tracing that can be trusted, we can
finally expect Nuitka to be generally fast and deserve to be called a
compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That will take a while, but it’s likely to happen in 2016. Let’s see if
I will get the funding to go to EuroPython 2016, that would be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nuitka.net/posts/nuitka-progress-winter-2015.html" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>For quite a bit, there have been no status posts, not for lack of news,
but a lot has happened indeed. I just seem to post a lot more to the
mailing list than I do here. Especially about unfinished stuff, which is
essentially for a project like Nuitka everything that’s going on.</summary>
    <category term="Python" label="Python"/>
    <category term="compiler" label="compiler"/>
    <category term="Nuitka" label="Nuitka"/>
    <category term="europython" label="europython"/>
    <published>2016-01-29T08:08:54+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
